Alternatives

There aren't really any alternatives to Ash that we are aware of that do all of the same things, but there are many different packages out there that do some of the things that Ash does.

This is a living document, and is not comprehensive. We are not vouching for any of these packages, but rather listing them here for your convenience to investigate on your own.

Want to add or edit this list? Open a pull request. Want a more comprehensive list? Check out the Awesome Elixir.

Application Frameworks

These frameworks have similar overarching goals of helping you build your application layer.

Commanded - An event sourced application framework.
Sleeky - Billed as a lightweight alternative to Ash. Inspired by Ash, but more tightly built on top of ecto.

Application Design

Boundary - A library for defining boundaries in your application.
Phoenix Contexts - Phoenix ships with a concept called "contexts", which provide some generators with application design guidance.

Building APIs

Absinthe - A GraphQL toolkit for Elixir. This is what AshGraphql uses under the hood, but you can also use Absinthe directly.
Phoenix - Phoenix is a web framework for Elixir. It is not necessarily an API framework, but has all the tools you need to build APIs by hand.
JSONAPI Elixir - A library for building JSONAPI compliant APIs in Elixir on top of Ecto.
Open API Spex - A library for generating OpenAPI (Swagger) documentation for your API. We generate these for you in AshJsonApi, but you can use this library to build open api specifications of your hand-written API

Working with Data

Ecto - Ecto is a database wrapper and query generator for Elixir. In many cases, Ash uses Ecto under the hood, but it is also available to build on top of directly.
Flop - A library designed to easily apply filtering, ordering, and pagination to Ecto queries.

Authentication

mix phx.gen.auth - A mix task that generates authentication for a Phoenix application. Some folks prefer to use this over AshAuthentication even if they are using Ash.
Assent - Multi-provider authentication framework.

Authorization

Bodyguard - A phoenix-context-based policy authorization framework.

Validation

Ecto - Ecto can be used to validate data at the edge, using things like schema-less changesets.
Drops - a collection of small modules that provide useful extensions and functions that can be used to work with data effectively.
GuardedStruct - validation, sanitization, and construction of structs, supporting nested structs.

Ash.Resource.Change.CascadeDestroy

Cascade a resource's destroy action to a related resource's destroy action.

Timing Control

The after_action? option controls when the cascade destroy occurs:

after_action?: true (default) - Runs as an after-action hook, making it safe for atomic actions
after_action?: false - Runs as a before-action hook

When after_action?: true, the change adds an after-action hook that explicitly calls destroy on any records related via the named relationship. It will optimise for bulk destroys where possible. This makes it safe to use in atomic actions, but might not be possible depending on the data layer setup (see warning below).

When after_action?: false, the change simply runs as a before_action. Requires keyset pagination on the primary read action of the targeted relation.

Beware database constraints

Think carefully before using this change with data layers which enforce referential integrity (ie PostgreSQL and SQLite) and you may need to defer constraints for the relationship in question.

See also:

postgres.references.reference.deferrable DSL
sqlite.references.reference.deferrable DSL
PostgreSQL's SET CONSTRAINTS documentation
SQLite's PRAGMA defer_foreign_keys documentation

Cascading notifications

By default notifications are disabled for the related destroy. This is to avoid potentially sending a lot of notifications for high-cardinality relationships.

Options

:relationship (atom/0) - Required. The name of the relationship to work on

:action (atom/0) - The name of the destroy action to call on the related resource. Uses the primary destroy by default.

:read_action (atom/0) - The name of the read action to call on the related resource to find results to be destroyed

:return_notifications? (boolean/0) - Return notifications for all destroyed records? The default value is false.

:after_action? (boolean/0) - If true, cascade destroys are done in after_action hooks. If false, they run as before_action hooks. Defaults to true for atomic action compatibility The default value is true.

Example

change {Ash.Resource.Change.CascadeDestroy, relationship: :comments, action: :destroy}

or, equivalently using Ash.Resource.Change.Builtins.cascade_destroy/2:

change cascade_destroy(:comments, action: :destroy)

Ash.Resource.Change.OptimisticLock

Apply an "optimistic lock" on a record being updated or destroyed.

What is Optimistic Locking?

Optimistic Locking is the process of only allowing an update to occur if the version of a record that you have in memory is the same as the version in the database. Otherwise, an error is returned. On success, it increments the version while performing the action.

Optimistic locking may used for two primary purposes:

User Experience

For example, if a user is editing a form that contains State and County fields, and they change the County, while another user has used the form to change the State, you could end up with a mismatch between State and County.

With optimistic locking, the user will instead get an error message that the record has been changed since they last looked.

Concurrency Safety

Optimistic locking can make actions safe to run concurrently even if they can't be performed in a single query (atomically), by returning an error if the resource in the data layer does not have the same version as the one being edited.

This tells the user that they need to reload and try again.

Design Principles

The design principles behind Ash allows us to build an extremely flexible and powerful set of tools, without locking users into specific choices at any level. The framework acts as a spinal cord for your application, with extension points at every level to allow for custom behavior. What follows are the core tenets behind Ash Framework.

Anything, not Everything

"Anything, not Everything" means building a framework capable of doing anything, not providing a framework that already does everything. The first is possible, the second is not. Our primary goal is to provide a framework that unlocks potential, and frees developers to work on the things that make their application special.

To this end, there are many prebuilt extensions to use, but there is also a rich suite of tools to build your own extensions. In this way, you can make the framework work for you, instead of struggling to fit your application to a strictly prescribed pattern. Use as much of Ash as you can, and leverage the amazing Elixir ecosystem for everything else.

Declarative, Introspectable, Derivable

The real superpower behind Ash is the declarative design pattern. All behavior is driven by explicit, static declarations. A resource, for example, is really just a configuration file. On its own it does nothing. It is provided to code that reads that configuration and acts accordingly.

You can read more about some simple declarative design patterns outside of the context of Ash Framework in An Incremental Approach to Declarative Design.

Configuration over Convention

While convention has value, we believe that explicit configuration ultimately leads to more discoverable, maintainable and flexible applications than a convention driven approach. This means that we never do things like assume that files with a given name are a certain type of thing, or that because a file is in a certain location, it should perform a specific function.

Pragmatism First

While Ash does have lofty goals and a roadmap, the priority for development is always what the current users of Ash need or are having trouble with. We focus on simple, pragmatic, and integrated solutions that meld well with the rest of the framework.

A high priority is placed on ensuring that our users don't experience feature whip-lash due to poorly thought out implementations, and that any breaking changes (a rare occurrence) have a clean and simple upgrade path. This is something made much easier by the declarative pattern.

Community

The Ash community comes together and collaborates to make sure that we can all build our software quickly, effectively and in a way that will age gracefully. We have a strict code of conduct, and love working with people of any experience level or background. To experience this first-hand, participate on ElixirForum or join our discord!

Domain Driven Design?

Ash is not a Domain Driven Design framework, if we're talking about "proper" Domain Driven Design as it is taught and discussed today. Domain Driven Design comes with a considerable amount of baggage and unnecessary complexity. While we identify with the goals of Domain Driven Design, we believe that a simpler approach is more effective, and that much of what DDD teaches are actually implementation details, and not design concepts. If the name wasn't taken, we would surely have claimed it for ourselves. If you must have a similar term for Ash, consider it a "Resource-oriented, Declarative Design Application Framework".

Destroy Actions

Destroy actions are comparatively simple. They expect to remove a given record, and by default return :ok in the successful case.

Most destroy actions are one-liners, for example:

destroy :destroy
# Can be added with the defaults
defaults [:read, :destroy]

Soft Destroy

You can mark a destroy action as soft? true, in which case it is handled by the update action logic.

For example:

destroy :archive do
  soft? true
  change set_attribute(:archived_at, &DateTime.utc_now/0)
end

For a full list of all of the available options for configuring destroy actions, see the Ash.Resource.Dsl documentation.

Calling Destroy Actions

The basic formula for calling a destroy action looks like this:

record
|> Ash.Changeset.for_destroy(:action_name, %{argument: :value}, ...opts)
|> Ash.destroy!()

See below for variations on action calling, and see the code interface guide guide for how to define idiomatic and convenient functions that call your actions.

Returning the destroyed record

You can use the return_destroyed? option to return the destroyed record.

# when a resource is passed, or a query w/ no action, the primary destroy action is used.
ticket = Ash.get!(Ticket, 1)
Ash.destroy!(ticket)
# => :ok
ticket = Ash.get!(Ticket, 2)
Ash.destroy!(ticket, return_destroyed?: true)
# => {:ok, %Ticket{}}

Loading on destroyed records

Keep in mind that using Ash.load on destroyed data will produced mixed results. Relationships may appear as empty, or may be loaded as expected (depending on the data layer/relationship implementation) and calculations/aggregates may show as nil if they must be run in the data layer.

Bulk Destroys

There are three strategies for bulk destroying data. They are, in order of preference: :atomic, :atomic_batches, and :stream. When calling Ash.bulk_destroy/4, you can provide a strategy or strategies that can be used, and Ash will choose the best one available. The capabilities of the data layer determine what strategies can be used.

Atomic

Atomic bulk destroys are used when the subject of the bulk destroy is a query and the data layer supports destroying a query. They map to a single statement to the data layer to destroy all matching records.

Example

Ticket
|> Ash.Query.filter(status == :open)
|> Ash.bulk_destroy!(:close, %{})

If using a SQL data layer, this would produce a query along the lines of

DELETE FROM tickets
WHERE status = 'open';

Atomic Batches

Atomic batches are used when the subject of the bulk destroy is an enumerable (i.e list or stream) of records and the data layer supports destroying a query. The records are pulled out in batches, and then each batch follows the logic described above. The batch size is controllable by the batch_size option.

Example

Ash.bulk_destroy!(one_hundred_tickets, :close, %{}, batch_size: 10)

If using a SQL data layer, this would produce ten queries along the lines of

DELETE FROM tickets
WHERE id IN (...ids)

Stream

Stream is used when the data layer does not support destroying a query. If a query is given, it is run and the records are used as an enumerable of inputs. If an enumerable of inputs is given, each one is destroyed individually. There is nothing inherently wrong with doing this kind of destroy, but it will naturally be slower than the other two strategies. The benefit of having a single interface (Ash.bulk_destroy/4) is that the caller doesn't need to change based on the performance implications of the action.

Check the docs!

Make sure to thoroughly read and understand the documentation in Ash.bulk_destroy/4 before using. Read each option and note the default values. By default, bulk destroys don't return records or errors, and don't emit notifications.

Destroying records

If you provide an enumerable of records, they will be destroyed in batches. For example:

Ash.bulk_destroy([%Ticket{}, %Ticket{}], :destroy, %{})

Destroying

Running the Destroy Action

All actions are run in a transaction if the data layer supports it. You can opt out of this behavior by supplying transaction?: false when creating the action. When an action is being run in a transaction, all steps inside of it are serialized because transactions cannot be split across processes.

Authorization is performed on the changes
A before action hook is added to set up belongs_to relationships that are managed. This means potentially creating/modifying the destination of the relationship, and then changing the destination_attribute of the relationship.
before_transaction and around_transaction hooks are called (Ash.Changeset.before_transaction/2). Keep in mind, any validations that are marked as before_action? true (or all global validations if your action has delay_global_validations? true) will not have happened at this point.
A transaction is opened if the action is configured for it (by default they are) and the data layer supports transactions
before_action hooks are performed in order
The main action is sent to the data layer
after_action hooks are performed in order
Non-belongs-to relationships are managed, creating/updating/destroying related records.
The transaction is closed, if one was opened
after_transaction hooks are invoked with the result of the transaction (even if it was an error)

Expressions

Ash expressions are used in various places like calculations, filters, and policies, and are meant to be portable representations of elixir expressions. You can create an expression using the Ash.Expr.expr/1 macro, like so:

Ash.Expr.expr(1 + 2)
Ash.Expr.expr(x + y)
Ash.Expr.expr(post.title <> " | " <> post.subtitle)

Ash Expressions are SQL-ish

Ash expressions have some interesting properties in their evaluation, primarily because they are made to be portable, i.e executable in some data layer (like SQL) or executable in Elixir. In general, these expressions will behave the same way they do in Elixir. The primary difference is how nil values work. They behave the way that NULL values behave in SQL. This is primarily because this pattern is easier to replicate to various popular data layers, and is generally safer when using expressions for things like authentication. The practical implications of this are that nil values will "poison" many expressions, and cause them to return nil. For example, x + nil would always evaluate to nil. Additionally, true and nil will always result in nil, this is also true with or and not, i.e true or nil will return nil, and not nil will return nil.

Additionally, atoms and strings compare as if the atom was a string. This is because most external data layers do not know about atoms, and so they are converted to strings before comparison.

Operators

The following operators are available and they behave the same as they do in Elixir, except for the nil addendum above.

==
!=
>
>=
<
<=
in
*
-
/
<>
and - Boolean and operator
or - Boolean or operator
|| - Elixir-ish or operator, if left is not nil or false, then left. Othewise right.
&& - Elixir-ish and operator, if left is not nil or false, then right. Otherwise left.

is_nil | Only works as an operator in maps/keyword list syntax. i.e [x: [is_nil: true]]

Elixir-ish operators

Prefer to use and and or if you are dealing with booleans, as they will typically perform much better in SQL data layers. && and || should only be used when you want to deal with more than boolaens.

For example:

calculate :identifier, expr(manual_identifier || employee_id <> " " <> location_code)

Functions

The following functions are built in. Data Layers can add their own functions to expressions. For example, AshPostgres adds trigram_similarity function.

The following functions are built in:

if | Works like elixir's if.

is_nil/1 | Works like elixir's is_nil

get_path/2 | i.e get_path(value, ["foo", "bar"]). This is what expressions like value[:foo]["bar"] are turned into under the hood.

contains/2 | if one string contains another string, i.e contains("fred", "red")

length/1 | the length of a list, i.e. length([:foo, :bar])

type/2 | Cast a given value to a specific type, i.e type(^arg(:id), :uuid) or type(integer_field, :string)

string_downcase/1 | Downcases a string

string_join/1 | Concatenates a list of strings, and ignores any nil values

string_join/2 | As above, but with a joiner

string_position/2 | Returns the zero-based position of a substring within a string, or nil, i.e. string_position("fred", "red") == 1

string_split/1 | Splits a string on spaces

string_split/2 | As above, but with a specific delimiter

string_split/3 | As above, but with options. See the function for the available options.

string_length/1 | Returns the length of a given string, as reported by String.length/1

string_trim/1 | Trims unicode whitespace from the beginning and the end of a string

at/2 | Get an element from a list, i.e at(list, 1)

round/1 | Round a float, decimal or int to 0 precision, i.e round(num)

round/2 | Round a float, decimal or int to the provided precision or less, i.e round(1.1234, 3) == 1.1234 and round(1.12, 3) == 1.12

String interpolation | "#{first_name} #{last_name}", is remapped to the equivalent usage of <>

fragment/* | Creates a fragment of a data layer expression. See the section on fragments below.

error/2 | Raises an error with a given exception module and parameters. See the section on error expressions below.

Fragments

Fragments come in two forms.

String Fragments

For SQL/query-backed data layers, they will be a string with question marks for interpolation. For example: fragment("(? + ?)", foo, bar).

Function Fragments

For elixir-backed data layers, they will be a function or an MFA that will be called with the provided arguments. For example: fragment(&Module.add/2, foo, bar) or fragment({Module, :add, []}, foo, bar). When using anonymous functions, you can only use the format &Module.function/arity. &Module.add/2 is okay, but fn a, b -> Module.add(a, b) end is not.

Sub-expressions

exists/2 | exists(foo.bar, name == "fred") takes an expression scoped to the destination resource, and checks if any related entry matches. See the section on exists below.

path.exists/2 | Same as exists but the source of the relationship is itself a nested relationship. See the section on exists below.

parent/1 | Allows an expression scoped to a resource to refer to the "outer" context. Used in relationship filters and exists

DateTime Functions

now/0 | Evaluates to the current time when the expression is evaluated

today/0 | Evaluates to the current date when the expression is evaluated

ago/2 | i.e deleted_at > ago(7, :day). The available time intervals are documented in Ash.Type.DurationName

from_now/2 | Same as ago but adds instead of subtracting

datetime_add/3 | add an interval to a datetime, i.e datetime_add(^datetime, 10, :hour)

date_add/3 | add an interval to a date, i.e date_add(^date, 3, :day)

start_of_day/1-2 | Converts a date or a datetime to the correspond start of its day (at 00:00 time).

Primitives

cond - cond is transformed to a series of if expressions under the hood
item[:key] or item["key"] - accesses keys in a map. In both cases, it prefers a matching atom key, falling back to a matching string key. This is to aid with data stores that store embeds as JSON with string keys (like AshPostgres), so that this expression behaves the same in the data layer as it does in Elixir.

Escape Hatches

lazy/1 - Takes an MFA and evaluates it just before running the query. This is important for calculations, because the expression/2 callback should be stable (returns the same value given the same input). For example lazy({ULID, :generate, [timestamp_input]})

Inline Aggregates

Aggregates can be referenced in-line, with their relationship path specified and any options provided that match the options given to Ash.Query.Aggregate.new/4. For example:

calculate :grade, :decimal, expr(
  count(answers, query: [filter: expr(correct == true)]) /
  count(answers, query: [filter: expr(correct == false)])
)

The available aggregate kinds can also be seen in the Ash.Query.Aggregate module documentation.

Templates

Most of the time, when you are using an expression, you will actually be creating a template. In this template, you have a few references that can be used, which will be replaced before the expression is evaluated. The following references are available:

^actor(:key) # equivalent to `get_in(actor || %{}, [:key])`
^actor([:key1, :key2]) # equivalent to `get_in(actor || %{}, [:key, :key2])`
^arg(:arg_name) # equivalent to `Map.get(arguments, :arg_name)`
^context(:key) # equivalent to `get_in(context, :key)`
^context([:key1, :key2]) # equivalent to `get_in(context, [:key1, :key2])`
^ref(:key) # equivalent to referring to `key`. Allows for dynamic references
^ref([:path], :key) # equivalent to referring to `path.key`. Allows for dynamic references with dynamic (or static) paths.

Custom Expressions

Custom expressions allow you to extend Ash's expression language with your own expressions. To see more, see Ash.CustomExpression. To add a custom expression, configure it and recompile ash. For example:

config :ash, :custom_expressions, [
  MyApp.CustomExpression
]

mix deps.compile ash --force

These expressions will be available across all usages of Ash expressions within your application.

Filter semantics & joins

The semantics of Ash filters are probably slightly different than what you are used to, and they are important to understand. Every filter expression is always talking about a single row, potentially "joined" to single related rows. By referencing relationships, you are implicitly doing a join. For those familiar with SQL terminology, it is equivalent to a left join, although AshPostgres can detect when it is safe to do an inner join (for performance reasons). Lets use an example of posts and comments.

Given a filter like the following:

Ash.Query.filter(Post, comments.points > 10 and comments.tag.name == "elixir")

The filter refers to a single post/comment/tag combination. So in english, this is "posts where they have a comment with more than 10 points and that same comment has a tag with the name elixir". What this also means is that filters like the above do not compose nicely when new filters are added. For example:

def has_comment_with_more_points_than(query, score) do
  Ash.Query.filter(query, comments.points > ^score)
end

def has_comment_tagged(query, tag) do
  Ash.Query.filter(query, comments.tag.name == ^tag)
end

Post
|> has_comment_with_more_points_than(10)
|> has_comment_tagged("elixir")

That code seems like it ought to produce a filter over Post that would give us any post with a comment having more than 10 points, and with a comment tagged elixir. That is not the same thing as having a single comment that meets both those criteria. So how do we make this better?

Many-to-many relationships

When working with expressions that join many-to-many relationships, there may be cases that you wish to refer to "the join row that connects these two things". For example, to sort a many-to-many relationship by the position on the join row. For this, we have special-cased references to parent(join_relationship_name) to refer to specifically the join row that connects the two records.

This allows for things like this:

many_to_many :tags, MyDomain.Tag do
  through MyDomain.PostTag
  join_relationship :post_tags
  sort [calc(parent(post_tags.position))]
end

Exists

Lets rewrite the above using exists:

def has_comment_with_more_points_than(query, score) do
  Ash.Query.filter(query, exists(comments, points > ^score))
end

def has_comment_tagged(query, tag) do
  Ash.Query.filter(query, exists(comments.tag, name == ^tag))
end

Post
|> has_comment_with_more_points_than(10)
|> has_comment_tagged("elixir")

Now, they will compose properly! Generally speaking, you should use exists when you are filtering across any relationships that are to_many relationships *even if you don't expect your filter to be composed. Currently, the filter syntax does not minimize(combine) these exists/2 statements, but doing so is not complex and can be added. While unlikely, please lodge an issue if you see any performance issues with exists.

Exists at path

Sometimes, you want the ability to say that some given row must have an existing related entry matching a filter. For example:

Ash.Query.filter(Post, author.exists(roles, name == :admin) and author.active)

While the above is not common, it can be useful in some specific circumstances, and is used under the hood by the policy authorizer when combining the filters of various resources to create a single filter.

Portability

Ash expressions being portable is more important than it sounds. For example, if you were using AshPostgres and had the following calculation, which is an expression capable of being run in elixir or translated to SQL:

calculate :full_name, :string, expr(first_name <> " " <> last_name)

And you did something like the following:

User
|> Ash.Query.load(:full_name)
|> Ash.Query.sort(:full_name)
|> Accounts.read!()

You would see that it ran a SQL query with the full_name calculation as SQL. This allows for sorting on that value. However, if you had something like this:

# data can be loaded in the query like above, or on demand later
Accounts.load!(user, :full_name, reuse_values?: true)

you would see that no SQL queries are run. The calculation is run directly in Elixir without needing to visit the database.

Parent

Parent is a way to "jump out" of a scoped expression. Here are some examples:

Ash.Query.filter(exists(open_tickets, severity >= parent(severity_threshold)))

has_many :relevant_tickets, Ticket do
  no_attributes? true
  # this says that there is no matching source_attribute and destination_attribute on this relationship
  filter expr(status == :open and severity >= parent(severity_threshold))
end

count :count_of_relevant_tickets, :open_tickets do
  filter expr(status == :open and severity >= parent(severity_threshold))
end

Referencing related values

Related values can be references using dot delimiters, i.e Ash.Query.filter(user.first_name == "fred"). When referencing related values in filters, if the reference is a has_one or belongs_to, the filter does exactly what it looks like (matches if the related value matches). If it is a has_many or a many_to_many, it matches if any of the related records match.

Referencing aggregates and calculations

Aggregates are simple, as all aggregates can be referenced in filter expressions (if you are using a data layer that supports aggregates).

For calculations, only those that define an expression can be referenced in other expressions.

Here are some examples:

# given a `full_name` calculation

Ash.Query.filter(User, full_name == "Hob Goblin")

# given a `full_name` calculation that accepts an argument called `delimiter`

Ash.Query.filter(User, full_name(delimiter: "~") == "Hob~Goblin")

Case vs Cond Expressions

When working with conditional expressions in Ash, you should use cond instead of case statements. Here's an example:

# This works - using cond
calculations do
  calculate :user_order, :integer, expr(
    cond do
      role == :principal -> 1
      role == :teacher -> 2
      role == :student -> 3
    end
  )
end

# This doesn't work - using case
calculations do
  calculate :user_order, :integer, expr(
    case role do
      :principal -> 1
      :teacher -> 2
      :student -> 3
    end
  )
end

The cond expression is the correct way to handle conditional logic in Ash expressions.

Error Expressions

The error/2 function is used within atomic validations, changes, and calculations to conditionally raise errors. It takes two arguments:

An exception module (typically an Ash error module)
A map of parameters for the exception

Basic Usage

error(Ash.Error.Changes.InvalidAttribute, %{
  field: :price,
  value: ^atomic_ref(:price),
  message: "must be greater than 0"
})

Common Pattern in Validations

The error/2 function is commonly used in atomic validations to produce errors when conditions are not met:

# In an atomic validation
{:atomic, [:price], expr(^atomic_ref(:price) <= 0),
 expr(
   error(^InvalidAttribute, %{
     field: :price,
     value: ^atomic_ref(:price),
     message: "must be greater than 0"
   })
 )}

Usage in Calculations for Unreachable Branches

The error/2 function is useful in calculations to handle cases that should never occur, making unreachable code paths explicit:

calculate :status_label, :string, expr(
  cond do
    status == :active -> "Active"
    status == :inactive -> "Inactive"
    status == :pending -> "Pending"
    true -> error(Ash.Error.Framework.AssumptionFailed, %{
      message: "Unexpected status value: %{status}",
      vars: %{status: status}
    })
  end
)

Example with Variables

You can include variables for message interpolation:

error(Ash.Error.Changes.InvalidChanges, %{
  message: "must be less than or equal to %{max}",
  vars: %{max: ^max}
})

Common Error Modules

Ash.Error.Changes.InvalidAttribute - Used for attribute validation errors
Ash.Error.Changes.InvalidChanges - Used for general change validation errors
Ash.Error.Changes.StaleRecord - Used for optimistic locking violations
Ash.Error.Framework.AssumptionFailed - Used for unreachable code or violated assumptions

Usage in Atomic Operations

The error/2 function is essential for atomic operations, allowing you to specify exactly what error should be raised when validation conditions fail:

# In a compare validation
atomic_update(:status, 
  expr(
    if ^atomic_ref(:score) > 100 do
      error(^InvalidAttribute, %{
        field: :score,
        value: ^atomic_ref(:score),
        message: "score cannot exceed 100"
      })
    else
      :valid
    end
  )
)

For more information about error handling in Ash, see the Error Handling guide.

Identities

Identities are a way to declare that a record (an instance of a resource) can be uniquely identified by a set of attributes. This information can be used in various ways throughout the framework. The primary key of the resource does not need to be listed as an identity.

Defining an identity

Identities are defined at the top level of a resource module, eg.

defmodule MyApp.MyResource do
  use Ash.Resource #, ...
  # ...

  identities do
    # If the `email` attribute must be unique across all records
    identity :unique_email, [:email]

    # If the `username` attribute must be unique for every record with a given `site` value
    identity :special_usernames, [:username, :site]

    # If the `user_id` field should hold the errors for the uniqueness violation
    identity :unique_email, [:email], field_names: [:user_id]
  end
end

See d:Ash.Resource.Dsl.identities for the full range of options available when defining identities.

Using Ash.get

This will allow these fields to be passed to Ash.get/3, e.g Ash.get(Resource, %{email: "foo"}).

Using upserts

Create actions support the upsert?: true option, if the data layer supports it. An upsert? involves checking for a conflict on some set of attributes, and translating the behavior to an update in the case one is found. By default, the primary key is used when looking for duplicates, but you can set [upsert?: true, upsert_identity: :identity_name] to tell it to look for conflicts on a specific identity.

Creating unique constraints

Tools like AshPostgres will create unique constraints in the database automatically for each identity. These unique constraints will honor other configuration on your resource, like the base_filter and attribute multitenancy

Eager Checking

Setting eager_check?: true on an identity will allow that identity to be checked when building a create changeset over the resource. This allows for showing quick up-front validations about whether some value is taken, for example. If the resource does not have the domain configured, you can specify the domain to use with eager_check_with: DomainName.

If you are using AshPhoenix.Form, for example, this looks for a conflicting record on each call to Form.validate/2. For updates, it is only checked if one of the involved fields is being changed.

For creates, The identity is checked unless your are performing an upsert, and the upsert_identity is this identity. Keep in mind that for this to work properly, you will need to pass the upsert?: true, upsert_identity: :identity_name when creating the changeset. The primary? read action is used to search for a record. This will error if you have not configured one.

Pre Checking

pre_check? behaves the same as eager_check?, but it runs just prior to the action being committed. Useful for data layers that don't support transactions/unique constraints, or manual resources with identities. Ash.DataLayer.Ets will require you to set pre_check? since the ETS data layer has no built in support for unique constraints. The domain can be manually specified with pre_check_with: DomainName.

mix ash.gen.resource

Generate and configure an Ash.Resource.

If the domain does not exist, we create it. If it does, we add the resource to it if it is not already present.

Example

mix ash.gen.resource Helpdesk.Support.Ticket \
  --default-actions read \
  --uuid-primary-key id \
  --attribute subject:string:required:public \
  --relationship belongs_to:representative:Helpdesk.Support.Representative \
  --timestamps \
  --extend postgres,graphql

Options

--attribute or -a - An attribute or comma separated list of attributes to add, as name:type. Modifiers: primary_key, array, public, sensitive, and required. i.e -a name:string:required
--relationship or -r - A relationship or comma separated list of relationships to add, as type:name:dest. Modifiers: public. belongs_to only modifiers: primary_key, sensitive, and required. i.e -r belongs_to:author:MyApp.Accounts.Author:required
--default-actions - A csv list of default action types to add. The create and update actions accept the public attributes being added.
--uuid-primary-key or -u - Adds a UUIDv4 primary key with that name. i.e -u id
--uuid-v7-primary-key - Adds a UUIDv7 primary key with that name.
--integer-primary-key or -i - Adds an integer primary key with that name. i.e -i id
--domain or -d - The domain module to add the resource to. i.e -d MyApp.MyDomain. This defaults to the resource's module name, minus the last segment.
--extend or -e - A comma separated list of modules or builtins to extend the resource with. i.e -e postgres,Some.Extension
--base or -b - The base module to use for the resource. i.e -b Ash.Resource. Requires that the module is in config :your_app, :base_resources
--timestamps or -t - If set adds inserted_at and updated_at timestamps to the resource.
--ignore-if-exists - Does nothing if the resource already exists
--conflicts - How to handle conflicts when the same attribute, relationship, or action already exists. Options: ignore (default), replace ignore will ignore your addition for that attribute, relationship, or action. replace will remove the existing one in favor of yours.

Monitoring

Monitoring in Ash has two primary components, Ash.Tracer and :telemetry. Monitoring might also be referred to as observability and instrumentation.

Packages

If you want to integrate with Appsignal, use the AshAppsignal package, which is maintained by the core team. We believe that Appsignal is a great way to get started quickly, is relatively cost effective, and provides a great user experience.

Telemetry

Ash emits the following telemetry events, suffixed with :start and :stop. Start events have system_time measurements, and stop events have system_time and duration measurements. All times will be in the native time unit.

Important

Note the mention of :start and :stop suffixes. The event below [:ash, (domain_short_name), :create], is actually referring to two events, [:ash, (domain_short_name), :create, :start] and [:ash, (domain_short_name), :create, :stop].

_Replace (domain_short_name) with your domain short name, from d:Ash.Domain.Info.short_name.

Events

[:ash, (domain_short_name), :create] - The execution of a create action. Use resource_short_name and action metadata to break down measurements.
[:ash, (domain_short_name), :update] - The execution of a update action. Use resource_short_name and action metadata to break down measurements.
[:ash, (domain_short_name), :read] - The execution of a read action. Use resource_short_name and action metadata to break down measurements.
[:ash, (domain_short_name), :destroy] - The execution of a destroy action. Use resource_short_name and action metadata to break down measurements.
[:ash, (domain_short_name), :action] - The execution of a generic action. Use resource_short_name and action metadata to break down measurements.
[:ash, :changeset] - A changeset being processed for a given action, i.e with Ash.Changeset.for_create. Use resource_short_name metadata to break down measurements.
[:ash, :query] - A query being processed for an action, with Ash.Query.for_read. Use resource_short_name metadata to break down measurements.
[:ash, :validation] - A validation being run on a changeset. Use resource_short_name and validation metadata to break down measurements.
[:ash, :change] - A change being run on a changeset. Use resource_short_name and change metadata to break down measurements.
[:ash, :calculation] - A calculation being computed in the app. Use resource_short_name and calculation metadata to break down measurements.
[:ash, :before_action] - A before_action being run on a changeset. Use resource_short_name to break down measurements.
[:ash, :after_action] - An after_action being run on a changeset. Use resource_short_name to break down measurements.
[:ash, :preparation] - A preparation being run on a changeset. Use resource_short_name and preparation metadata to break down measurements.
[:ash, :notifier] - A notifier being run with a notification. Use resource_short_name and notifier metadata to break down measurements.
[:ash, :request_step] - The resolution of an internal request. Ash breaks up its operations internally into multiple requests, this can give you a high resolution insight onto the execution of those internal requests resolution. Use name metadata to break down measurements.

Tracing

Tracing is very similar to telemetry, but gives you some additional hooks to set_span_context() and get_span_context(). This allows you to "move" some piece of context between two processes. Ash will call this whenever it starts a new process to do anything. What this means is that if you are using a tracing tool or library you can ensure that any processes spawned by Ash are properly included in the trace. Additionally, you should be able to integrate a tracing library to include Ash actions/spans relatively easily by implementing the other callbacks.

A tracer can be configured globally in application config.

config :ash, :tracer, MyApp.Tracer

Additionally, one can be provide when creating changesets or calling an action, i.e

Resource
# better to put it here, as changesets are traced as well. It will be carried over to the domain action
|> Ash.Changeset.for_create(:create, %{}, tracer: MyApp.Tracer)
# but you can also pass it here.
|> Ash.create!(tracer: MyApp.Tracer)

For customizing the names created for each span, see:

d:Ash.Domain.Dsl.execution|trace_name
d:Ash.Resource.Dsl.resource|trace_name

Trace types

These are the list of trace types.

:custom
:action
:changeset
:validation
:change
:calculation
:before_transaction
:before_action
:after_transaction
:after_action
:request_step
:query
:notifier
:preparation
:preparation

After/Before Action Hooks

Due to the way before/after action hooks run, their execution time won't be included in the span created for the change. In practice, before/after action hooks are where the long running operations tend to be. We start a corresponding span and emit a telemetry event for before and after hooks, but they are only so useful. In a trace, they can highlight that "some hook" took a long time. In telemetry metrics they are of even less use. The cardinality of the metric would be extremely high, and we don't have a "name" or anything to distinguish them. To that end, you can use the macros & functions available in Ash.Tracer to create custom spans and/or emit custom telemetry events from your hooks. They automatically handle cases where the provided tracer is nil, for convenience. For example:

defmodule MyApp.CustomChange do
  use Ash.Resource.Change

  require Ash.Tracer

  def change(changeset, _, _) do
    changeset
    |> Ash.Changeset.before_action(fn changeset ->
      Ash.Tracer.span(:custom, "custom name", changeset.context[:private][:tracer]) do
        # optionally set some metadata
        metadata = %{...}
        Ash.Tracer.set_metadata(changeset.context[:private][:tracer], :custom, metadata)
        # will get `:start` and `:stop` suffixed events emitted
        Ash.Tracer.telemetry_span([:telemetry, :event, :name], metadata) do
          ## Your logic here
        end
      end
    end)
  end
end

Policies

Policies determine what actions on a resource are permitted for a given actor, and can also filter the results of read actions to restrict the results to only records that should be visible.

To restrict access to specific fields (attributes, aggregates, calculations), see the section on field policies.

Read and understand the Actors & Authorization guide before proceeding, which explains actors, how to set them, and other relevant configurations.

Setup

You'll need to add the extension to your resource, like so:

use Ash.Resource, authorizers: [Ash.Policy.Authorizer]

Then you can start defining policies for your resource.

Policies

Anatomy of a Policy

Each policy defined in a resource has two parts -

a condition or a list of conditions, such as action_type(:read), [action_type(:read), actor_attribute_equals(:admin, true)] or always(). If the condition, or all conditions if given a list are true for a given action request, then the policy will be applied to the request.
a set of policy checks, each of which will be evaluated individually if a policy applies to a request.

If more than one policy applies to any given request (eg. an admin actor calls a read action) then all applicable policies must pass for the action to be performed.

A policy will produce one of three results: :forbidden, :authorized, or :unknown. :unknown is treated the same as :forbidden.

The Simplest Policy

Let's start with the simplest (most permissive) policy:

policies do
  policy always() do
    authorize_if always()
  end
end

The first argument to policy is the condition. In this case, the condition is always() - a built-in helper always returning true, meaning that the policy applies to every request.

Within this policy we have a single policy check, declared with authorize_if. Checks logically apply from top to bottom, based on their check type. In this case, we'd read the policy as "this policy always applies, and authorizes always".

There are four check types, all of which do what they sound like they do:

authorize_if - if the check is true, the whole policy is authorized.
authorize_unless - if the check is false, the whole policy is authorized.
forbid_if - if the check is true, the whole policy is forbidden.
forbid_unless - if the check is false, the whole policy is forbidden.

If a single check does not explicitly authorize or forbid the whole policy, then the flow moves to the next check. For example, if an authorize_if check does NOT return true, this does not mean the whole policy is forbidden - it means that further checking is required.

Policy with condition inside do block

A condition or a list of conditions can also be moved inside the policy block.

This can make a really long list of conditions easier to read.

policies do
  policy do
    condition always()
    authorize_if always()
  end
end

How a Decision is Reached

Not every check in a policy must pass! This is described above, but is very important so another example is provided here. Checks go from top to bottom, are evaluated independently of each other, and the first one that reaches a decision determines the overall policy result. For example:

policy action_type(:create) do
  authorize_if IsSuperUser
  forbid_if Deactivated
  authorize_if IsAdminUser
  forbid_if RegularUserCanCreate
  authorize_if RegularUserAuthorized
end

We check those from top to bottom, so the first one of those that returns :authorized or :forbidden determines the entire outcome. For example:

authorize_if IsSuperUser # If this is true, the actor is a superuser

# None of the rest of the checks matter, even if the actor is deactivated.
forbid_if Deactivated
authorize_if IsAdminUser
forbid_if RegularUserCanCreate
authorize_if RegularUserAuthorized

Conversely:

authorize_if IsSuperUser # This can be false
forbid_if Deactivated # This can be false
authorize_if IsAdminUser # If this is true, then the policy is still authorized.

# And none of these checks matter
forbid_if RegularUserCanCreate
authorize_if RegularUserAuthorized

Not all policy checks have yes/no answers

This will be covered in greater detail in Checks, but will be briefly mentioned here.

Ash provides two basic types of policy checks - simple checks and filter checks. Simple checks are what we commonly think of with authorization, and what the above example would suggest - is an actor allowed to perform a given operation, yes or no? But we can also use filter checks - given a list of resources, which ones is an actor allowed to perform the operation on?

Filter checks are applied to all read actions, including those generated for bulk updates and destroys.

Read Actions and Filtering Behavior

An important characteristic of read actions is that, by default, they are filtered by policies rather than returning authorization errors. This means:

When a user is not allowed to see certain records, those records are simply filtered out of the results
Instead of receiving a Forbidden error, users typically get a NotFound error (for single record queries) or an empty/reduced result set (for multi-record queries)
This filtering behavior applies to all read actions, including get, read, and any custom read actions you define

For example, if a policy restricts users to only see their own posts, a query for all posts will automatically filter to only return the current user's posts, rather than raising an authorization error. Similarly, attempting to fetch a specific post that belongs to another user will result in a NotFound error rather than Forbidden.

This design is a security feature that prevents enumeration attacks and information disclosure. By not distinguishing between "record doesn't exist" and "record exists but you can't access it", the system prevents attackers from probing to discover the existence of protected data, mapping out the system's data structure, or conducting reconnaissance attacks through systematic querying.

Bypassing this behavior

You can bypass this behavior on a case-by-case basis with the authorize_with option, for data layers that support error expressions (all of the core ones except AshSqlite).

For example, given a post that the user cannot see:

Ash.get!(Post, 123)
# * Invalid:
# not found

Ash.get!(Post, 123, authorize_with: :error)
# * Forbidden

Bypass policies

A bypass policy is just like a regular policy, except if a bypass passes, then other policies after it do not need to pass. This can be useful for writing complex access rules, or for a simple rule like "an admin can do anything" without needing to specify it as part of every other policy.

A realistic policy

In this example, we use some of the provided built-in checks.

policies do
  # Anything you can use in a condition, you can use in a check, and vice-versa
  # This policy applies if the actor is a super_user
  # Additionally, this policy is declared as a `bypass`. That means that this check is allowed to fail without
  # failing the whole request, and that if this check *passes*, the entire request passes.
  bypass actor_attribute_equals(:super_user, true) do
    authorize_if always()
  end

  # This will likely be a common occurrence. Specifically, policies that apply to all read actions
  policy action_type(:read) do
    # unless the actor is an active user, forbid
    forbid_unless actor_attribute_equals(:active, true)
    # if the record is marked as public, authorize
    authorize_if expr(public == true)
    # if the actor is related to the data via that data's `owner` relationship, authorize
    authorize_if relates_to_actor_via(:owner)
  end
end

Policy Groups

Policy groups are a small abstraction over policies, that allow you to group policies together that have shared conditions. Each policy inside of a policy group have the same conditions as their group.

policies do
  policy_group actor_attribute_equals(:role, :owner) do
    policy action_type(:read) do
      authorize_if expr(owner_id == ^actor(:id))
    end

    policy action_type([:update, :destroy]) do
      authorize_if expr(owner_id == ^actor(:id))
    end

    policy action_type(:create) do
      authorize_if relating_to_actor(:owner)
    end
  end
end

Nesting Policy groups

Policy groups can be nested. This can help when you have lots of policies and conditions.

policies do
  policy_group condition do
    policy_group condition2 do
       policy condition3 do
         # This policy applies if condition, condition2, and condition3 are all true
       end
    end
  end
end

Bypasses

Policy groups can not contain bypass policies. The purpose of policy groups is to make it easier to reason about the behavior of policies. When you see a policy group, you know that no policies inside that group will interact with policies in other policy groups, unless they also apply.

Access Type

Policies have an "access type" that determines when they are applied. By default, access_type is :filter. When applied to a read action, :filter will result in a filtered read. For other action types, the filter will be evaluated to determine if a forbidden error should be raised.

There are three access types, and they determine the latest point in the process that any check contained by a policy can be applied.

strict - All checks must be applied statically. These result in a forbidden error if they are not met.
filter - All checks must be applied either statically or as a filter. These result in a filtered read if they are not met, and a forbidden error for other action types.
runtime - This allows checks to be run after the data has been read. It is exceedingly rare that you would need to use this access type.

For example, given this policy:

policy action(:read_hidden) do
  authorize_if actor_attribute_equals(:is_admin, true)
end

A non-admin using the :read_hidden action would see an empty list of records, rather than a forbidden error.

However, with this policy

policy action(:read_hidden) do
  access_type :strict

  authorize_if actor_attribute_equals(:is_admin, true)
end

A non-admin using the :read_hidden action would see a forbidden error.

Relationships and Policies

A common point of confusion when working with relationships is when they return less results or no results due to policies. Additionally, when requesting related data that produces a forbidden error, it forbids the entire request.

For example, if you have a Post, that belongs_to :author, and the user requesting data cannot see the author due to a filter policy, then you may see something like this:

%MyApp.Post{author: nil, ...}

Even though it is not possible for a Post to exist without an associated :author!

Additionally, if the user cannot read the author due to a :strict policy, if you attempt to load the :author, the result of the entire operation will be {:error, %Ash.Error.Forbidden{}}.

There are two ways that you can improve this behavior

The allow_forbidden_field? Option

This option will default to true in 4.0. You can adopt this behavior now with the following configuration.

config :ash, :allow_forbidden_field_for_relationships_by_default?, true

This option adjusts the relationship reading logic such that, if running a related read action would produce a forbidden error, the relationship will be set to %Ash.ForbiddenField{}, instead of forbidding the entire request.

So in the example above where the entire operation fails, you would instead get:

{:ok, %MyApp.Post{author: %Ash.ForbiddenField{}}}

The authorize_read_with Option

This option typically only makes sense to apply on has_one and belongs_to relationships. This alters the behavior of policy filtering when loading related records. In our above example, lets say there is a policy like the following on MyApp.Author, that prevents us from reading an author that has been deactivated.

policy action_type(:read) do
  access_type :filter # This is the default access type. It is here for example.
  authorize_if expr(active == false)
end

When running a normal read action against that resource, you want any deactivated authors to be filtered out. However, when reading the :author relationship, you don't want the author to appear as nil. This is especially useful when combined with allow_forbidden_field? true.

So lets make our belongs_to relationship looks like this.

belongs_to :author, MyApp.Author do
  allow_nil? false
  allow_forbidden_field? true
  authorize_read_with :error
end

Now, that filter will be applied in such a way that produces an error if any record exists that matches not(active == false).

So a forbidden read of the :author relationship will never produce a nil value, nor will it produce an {:error, %Ash.Error.Forbidden{}} result. Instead, the value of :author will be %Ash.ForbiddenField{}!

Checks

Checks evaluate from top to bottom within a policy. A check can produce one of three results, the same that a policy can produce. While checks are not necessarily evaluated in order, they logically apply in that order, so you may as well think of it in that way. It can be thought of as a step-through algorithm.

For each check, starting from the top:

Run the check.

If it returns :authorized, the policy is :authorized
If it returns :forbidden, the policy is :forbidden
If it returns :unknown, the next check down is checked

For the example from earlier:

authorize_if IsSuperUser

If this check succeeds, it returns :authorized, the whole policy is :authorized, and checks stop running
If this check fails, it returns :unknown and the next check is checked

forbid_if Deactivated

We only care about this result if the previous check failed, ie. the actor is not a super user.
If this check succeeds, it returns :forbidden, the whole policy is :forbidden, and checks stop running
If this check fails, it returns :unknown and the next check is checked

authorize_if IsAdminUser

We only care about this result if the previous checks failed, ie. the actor is not a super user and is not deactivated.
If this check succeeds, it returns :authorized, the whole policy is :authorized and checks stop running.
If this check fails, it returns :unknown and the next check is checked

authorize_if RegularUserAuthorized

We only care about this result if the previous checks failed, ie. the actor is not a super user, not deactivated and not an admin user.
If this check succeeds, it returns :authorized, the whole policy is :authorized and checks stop running.
If this check fails, it returns :unknown. As there are no more checks to run, the whole policy returns :unknown, which is treated as forbidden and the actor is not allowed to perform the action.

Types of checks

As mentioned earlier, there are two distinct types of checks - simple checks and filter checks. So far we've seen examples of both - let's look in a bit more detail.

Manual Checks

Both simple and filter checks are a subset of a third type of check - a manual check - but you will almost always want to write simple or filter checks.

Simple checks

Simple checks are determined at the outset of a request, and can only cause a request to be authorized or forbidden. These are typically yes/no questions - is the actor an admin? Did the actor create the post they want to call the update action on? Is the actor old enough to drink alcohol?

You can write a simple check by creating a new module and using the Ash.Policy.SimpleCheck module:

defmodule MyApp.Checks.ActorIsOldEnough do
  use Ash.Policy.SimpleCheck

  # This is used when logging a breakdown of how a policy is applied - see Logging below.
  def describe(_) do
    "actor is old enough"
  end

  # The context here may have a changeset, query, resource, and domain module, depending
  # on the action being run.
  # `match?` should return true or false, and answer the statement being posed in the description,
  # i.e "is the actor old enough?"
  def match?(%MyApp.User{age: age} = _actor, %{resource: MyApp.Beer} = _context, _opts) do
    age >= 21
  end

  def match?(_, _, _), do: false
end

You can then use this module as the check name, as part of a policy:

defmodule MyApp.Beer do
  # ...

  policies do
    policy action(:drink) do
      authorize_if MyApp.Checks.ActorIsOldEnough
    end
  end

  # ...
end

Ash will internally convert the true/false return value from match?/3 to a :authorized/:forbidden/:unknown response, depending on how the check is being run (ie. whether it's part of an authorize_if/forbid_if/etc.)

Filter checks

Many checks won't return a status yes/no, but instead return a "filter" to apply to a collection of data. They are most commonly used for read actions, but can be used for all types of actions.

For update and destroy actions, they apply to the data before the action is run.

For read actions, they will automatically restrict the returned data to be compliant with the filter. Using the drinking example from earlier, we could write a filter check to list only users that are old enough to drink alcohol.

There are two ways to write a filter check - by creating a module and using the Ash.Policy.FilterCheck module, or by using inline expression syntax.

defmodule MyApp.Checks.ActorOverAgeLimit do
  use Ash.Policy.FilterCheck

  # A description is not necessary, as it will be derived from the filter, but one could be added
  # def describe(_opts), do: "actor is over the age limit"

  def filter(actor, _authorizer, _opts) do
    expr(age_limit <= ^actor.age)
  end
end

You can then use this module as the check name, as part of a policy:

defmodule MyApp.User do
  # ...

  policies do
    policy action(:of_drinking_age) do
      authorize_if MyApp.Checks.ActorOverAgeLimit
    end
  end

  # ...
end

Inline checks

Inline checks are filter checks, but are different enough to warrant their own documentation. These are written directly in a policy, eg.

policy action_type(:read) do
  # Allow records with the attribute `public` set to true to be read
  authorize_if expr(public == true)

  # Allow records with the attribute `level` less than the value of the `level`
  # argument to the action to be read
  authorize_if expr(level <= ^arg(:level))
end

Inline checks for create actions

When using expressions inside of policies that apply to create actions, you may not reference the data being created. For example:

policy action_type(:create) do
  # This check is fine, as we only reference the actor
  authorize_if expr(^actor(:admin) == true)
  # This check is not, because it contains a reference to a field
  authorize_if expr(status == :active)
end

Why can't we reference data in creates?

We cannot allow references to the data being created in create policies, because we do not yet know what the result of the action will be. For updates and destroys, referencing the data always references the data prior to the action being run, and so it is deterministic.

If a policy that applies to creates, would result in a filter, you will get a Ash.Error.Forbidden.CannotFilterCreates at runtime explaining that you must change your check. Typically this means writing a custom Ash.Policy.SimpleCheck instead.

Ash also comes with a set of built-in helpers for writing inline checks - see Ash.Policy.Check.Builtins for more information.

Referencing the actor

In expression checks, the actor template can be used (other templates that may work in filter expressions, for example, are not available). For example:

# Authorize records that have an author relationship with the author ID the same as the actor ID
# ie. records authored by the actor
authorize_if expr(author.id == ^actor(:id))

Using exists

A common mistake when using related data in filters is to be too restrictive. Imagine a scenario where you have an action like this:

read :friends_of_ted do
  filter expr(friends.first_name == "ted")
end

If this was in a User resource, it would return users that have a friend with the first name "ted". So far so good. Then someone calls it like so:

Resource
|> Ash.Query.for_read(:friends_of_ted)
|> Ash.Query.filter(friends.last_name == "dansen")

The resulting filter is friends.first_name == "ted" and friends.last_name == "dansen"- this means that you'll get users that have a friend with the full name "ted dansen". That might be what you meant, but more likely you would want "users that have a friend with the first name "ted", that also have a friend with the last name 'dansen'".

To accomplish that, we can use the exists helper and rework the example like so:

# There exists a friend with the first name "ted"
read :friends_of_ted do
  filter expr(exists(friends, first_name == "ted"))
end

# And there also exists a friend with the last name "dansen"
# They may be the same friend if the user is friends with Ted Dansen!
Resource
|> Ash.Query.for_read(:friends_of_ted)
|> Ash.Query.filter(exists(friends, last_name == "dansen"))

In policies (and often any time you mean "a related thing exists where some condition is true"), it is advised to use exists/2 when referring to relationships because of the way that the policy authorizer may mix & match your policies when building filters. This is also true when adding filters to actions. If you use exists, then your policies can be used in filters without excluding unnecessary data.

Field Policies

Field policies allow you to authorize access to specific fields via policies scoped to fields.

For example:

field_policies do
  field_policy :role do
    authorize_if actor_attribute_equals(:role, :supervisor)
  end
end

If any field policies exist then all fields must be authorized by a field policy. If you want a "deny-list" style, then you can add policies for specific fields. and add a catch-all policy using the special field name :*. All policies that apply to a field must be authorized.

The only exception to the above behavior is primary keys, which can always be read by everyone.

Additionally, keep in mind that adding Ash.Policy.Authorizer will require that all actions pass policies. If you want to just add field policies, you will need to add a policy that allows all access explicitly, i.e

policies do
  policy always() do
    authorize_if always()
  end
end

Using Expressions In Field Policies

Unlike in regular policies, expressions in field policies cannot refer to related entities currently (except when using exists). Instead, you will need to create aggregates or expression calculations that return the results you want to reference.

In results, forbidden fields will be replaced with a special value: %Ash.ForbiddenField{}.

When these fields are referred to in filters, they will be replaced with an expression that evaluates to nil. To support this behavior, only simple and filter checks are allowed in field policies.

Handling private fields in internal functions

When calling internal functions like Ash.read!/1, private fields will by default always be shown. Even if field policies apply to the resource. You can change the default behaviour by setting the private_fields option on field policies.

field_policies do
  private_fields :include
end

The different options are:

:show will always show private fields
:hide will always hide private fields
:include will let you to write field policies for private fields and private fields will be shown or hidden depending on the outcome of the policy

If you want to overwrite the default option that is :show, you can do that by setting a global flag:

config :ash, :policies, private_fields: :include

References to related data & fields

Calculations

The dependencies of a calculation do not have any authorization applied to them. This includes the dependencies loaded with Ash.Resource.Calculation.load/3, as well as any dependencies referenced in a calculation expression. To understand why this is the case, take the following calculation:

calculate :users_ssn_last_4, :string, expr(fragment("RIGHT(?, 4)", user.ssn))

The user record may not be visible to the actor loading this calculation, and if it is, the ssn field may not be visible due to field policies. If calculations authorized access to their dependencies, you would never be able to write a calculation like the above.

Aggregates

Aggregates are the one exception to the above. Aggregates referenced anywhere will always authorize access to the related data they reference (unless authorize?: false is set when running the action). They will not, however, authorize references to the actual field that they refer to. For example, you may not allow managers to see the email of their team members, but they are allowed to know something like "how many team members have set up their email". So in an aggregate like the following:

aggregate :users_with_email, :count, :email

if the field policies were applied to :email, that number would always show 0, because all :email attributes would appear to be nil to the manager.

Fields annotated as input

When you use Ash.Query.filter_input or Ash.Query.sort_input (which extensions like AshGraphql and AshJsonApi do when filters/sorts are provided by the user), the contained field references are annotated as input. The following rules are honored for field references annotated as input only. Per the above section, the contents of a calculation's expression referenced in filters are never annotated as input, although the calculation itself will be, so that you can write field policies on calculations.

Relationship paths in filters

When a field is referenced at a relationship path, the authorization rules for that related resource's primary read action (or the relationship's configured :read_action) will be applied to the filter as well. For example, say that you have a User resource, and a Post resource. The User resource can only be read by the actor if their id matches the user's id (i.e they can only read themselves).

These policies might look like this:

# on `User`
policy action_type(:read) do
  authorize_if expr(id == ^actor(:id))
end

Given a filter like Ash.Query.filter_input(Post, %{user: %{email: "example@example.com"}}), the resulting filter expression would be:

expr(
  user.email == "example@example.com" and
    user.id == ^actor(:id)
)

This prevents a common security vulnerability that would allow malicious actors to "sniff" related data by providing filters over User, and seeing what Post records are returned.

Field references in filters & sorts

When a field is referenced in filters or sorts, the field reference is replaced with a conditional, that evaluates to the field value if the actor is authorized to view the field, or nil otherwise (causing all conditions to evaluate to false).

Lets say that users have a field policy that only allows viewing the email address if the user's id matches the actor's id, similar to the abvoe example.

field_policies do
  field_policy :email, always() do
    authorize_if expr(user.id == ^actor(:id))
  end
end

When that field is referenced in filters or sorts, like so: Ash.Query.filter_input(Post, %{user: %{email: "example@example.com"}}), the resulting expression would become:

expr(
  if user.id == ^actor(:id) do
    user.email
  else
    nil
  end == "example@example.com"
)

This prevents the same security vulnerability as described above, which would allow malicious actors to "sniff" field values that should not be visible to them by providing filters and/or sorts that reference that field.

Debugging and Logging

Policy Breakdowns

Policy breakdowns can be fetched on demand for a given forbidden error (either an Ash.Error.Forbidden that contains one or more Ash.Error.Forbidden.Policy errors, or an Ash.Error.Forbidden.Policy error itself), via Ash.Error.Forbidden.Policy.report/2.

Additionally, you can request that they be provided in the error message for all raised forbidden errors (without the help text), by setting

config :ash, :policies, show_policy_breakdowns?: true

Here is an example policy breakdown from tests.

Policy Breakdown
A check status of `?` implies that the solver did not need to determine that check.
Some checks may look like they failed when in reality there was no need to check them.
Look for policies with `` and `` in check statuses.

A check with a `` means that it didn't determine if the policy was authorized or forbidden, and so moved on to the next check.
`` and `` mean that the check was responsible for producing an authorized or forbidden (respectively) status.

If no check results in a status (they all have ``) then the policy is assumed to have failed. In some cases, however, the policy
may have just been ignored, as described above.

  Admins and managers can create posts | :
    authorize if: actor.admin == true |  | 
    authorize if: actor.manager == true |  | 

To remove the help text, you can pass the help_text?: false option, which would leave you with:

Policy Breakdown
  Admins and managers can create posts | :
    authorize if: actor.admin == true |  | 
    authorize if: actor.manager == true |  | 

Including in error messages

IMPORTANT WARNING: The following configuration should only ever be used in development mode!

For security reasons, authorization errors don't include any extra information, aside from forbidden. To have authorization errors include a policy breakdown (without help text) use the following config.

config :ash, :policies, show_policy_breakdowns?: true

Logging

It is generally safe to log authorization error details, even in production. This can be very helpful when investigating certain classes of issue.

Global Logging Configuration

To have Ash automatically log each authorization failure, use

config :ash, :policies, log_policy_breakdowns: :error # Use whatever log level you'd like to use here

To have Ash log all policy breakdowns, even successful ones (this will be lots of noise, and should only be used for dev testing)

config :ash, :policies, log_successful_policy_breakdowns: :error # Use whatever log level you'd like to use here

Per-Request Logging

You can also enable logging for individual authorization checks by using the log? option with Ash.can/3 and Ash.can?/3:

# Log the authorization result for this specific check
Ash.can?(Post, :read, current_user, log?: true)

# This will log at info level when authorization succeeds or fails
MyDomain.can_read_post?(current_user, post, log?: true)

When log?: true is set, authorization results will be logged at the :info level regardless of the global logging configuration. This is useful for debugging specific authorization issues without enabling verbose logging globally.

Relationships

Relationships describe the connections between resources and are a core component of Ash. Defining relationships enables you to do things like

Loading related data
Filtering on related data
Managing related records through changes on a single resource
Authorizing based on the state of related data

Relationships Basics

A relationship exists between a source resource and a destination resource. These are defined in the relationships block of the source resource. For example, if MyApp.Tweet is the source resource, and MyApp.User is the destination resource, we could define a relationship called :owner like this:

defmodule MyApp.Tweet do
  use Ash.Resource,
    data_layer: my_data_layer

  attributes do
    uuid_primary_key :id
    attribute :body, :string
  end

  relationships do
    belongs_to :owner, MyApp.User
  end
end

Kinds of relationships

There are four kinds of relationships:

belongs_to
has_one
has_many
many_to_many

Each of these relationships has a source resource and a destination resource with a corresponding attribute on the source resource (source_attribute), and destination resource (destination_attribute). Relationships will validate that their configured attributes exist at compile time.

You don't need to have a corresponding "reverse" relationship for every relationship, i.e if you have a MyApp.Tweet resource with belongs_to :user, MyApp.User you aren't required to have a has_many :tweets, MyApp.Tweet on MyApp.User. All that is required is that the attributes used by the relationship exist.

Belongs To

# on MyApp.Tweet
belongs_to :owner, MyApp.User

A belongs_to relationship means that there is an attribute (source_attribute) on the source resource that uniquely identifies a record with a matching attribute (destination_attribute) in the destination. In the example above, the source attribute on MyApp.Tweet is :owner_id and the destination attribute on MyApp.User is :id.

Attribute Defaults

By default, the source_attribute is defined as :<relationship_name>_id of the type :uuid on the source resource and the destination_attribute is assumed to be :id. You can override the attribute names by specifying the source_attribute and destination_attribute options like so:

belongs_to :owner, MyApp.User do
  # defaults to :<relationship_name>_id (i.e. :owner_id)
  source_attribute :custom_attribute_name

  # defaults to :id
  destination_attribute :custom_attribute_name
end

You can further customize the source_attribute using options such as:

d:Ash.Resource.Dsl.relationships.belongs_to|define_attribute? to define it yourself
d:Ash.Resource.Dsl.relationships.belongs_to|attribute_type to modify the default type
d:Ash.Resource.Dsl.relationships.belongs_to|attribute_public? to make the source attribute public?: true

For example:

belongs_to :owner, MyApp.User do
  attribute_type :integer
  attribute_writable? false
end

Or if you wanted to define the attribute yourself,

attributes do
  attribute :owner_foo, MyApp.CustomType
end

...
relationships do
  belongs_to :owner, MyApp.User do
    define_attribute? false
    source_attribute :owner_foo
  end
end

Customizing default belongs_to attribute type

Destination attributes that are added by default are assumed to be :uuid. To change this, set the following configuration in config.exs:

config :ash, :default_belongs_to_type, :integer

See the docs for more: d:Ash.Resource.Dsl.relationships.belongs_to

Has One

# on MyApp.User
has_one :profile, MyApp.Profile

A has_one relationship means that there is a unique attribute (destination_attribute) on the destination resource that identifies a record with a matching unique attribute (source_resource) in the source. In the example above, the source attribute on MyApp.User is :id and the destination attribute on MyApp.Profile is :user_id.

A has_one is similar to a belongs_to except the reference attribute is on the destination resource, instead of the source.

Attribute Defaults

By default, the source_attribute is assumed to be :id, and destination_attribute defaults to <snake_cased_last_part_of_module_name>_id.

See the docs for more: d:Ash.Resource.Dsl.relationships.has_one

Has Many

# on MyApp.User
has_many :tweets, MyApp.Tweet

A has_many relationship means that there is a non-unique attribute (destination_attribute) on the destination resource that identifies a record with a matching attribute (source_attribute) in the source. In the example above, the source attribute on MyApp.User is :id and the destination attribute on MyApp.Tweet is :user_id.

A has_many relationship is similar to a has_one because the reference attribute exists on the destination resource. The only difference between this and has_one is that the destination attribute is not unique, and therefore will produce a list of related items. In the example above, :tweets corresponds to a list of MyApp.Tweet records.

Attribute Defaults

By default, the source_attribute is assumed to be :id, and destination_attribute defaults to <snake_cased_last_part_of_module_name>_id.

See the docs for more: d:Ash.Resource.Dsl.relationships.has_many

Many To Many

A many_to_many relationship can be used to relate many source resources to many destination resources. To achieve this, the source_attribute and destination_attribute are defined on a join resource. A many_to_many relationship can be thought of as a combination of a has_many relationship on the source/destination resources and a belongs_to relationship on the join resource.

For example, consider two resources MyApp.Tweet and MyApp.Hashtag representing tweets and hashtags. We want to be able to associate a tweet with many hashtags, and a hashtag with many tweets. To do this, we could define the following many_to_many relationship:

# on MyApp.Tweet
many_to_many :hashtags, MyApp.Hashtag do
  through MyApp.TweetHashtag
  source_attribute_on_join_resource :tweet_id
  destination_attribute_on_join_resource :hashtag_id
end

The through option specifies the "join" resource that will be used to store the relationship. We need to define this resource as well:

defmodule MyApp.TweetHashtag do
  use Ash.Resource,
    data_layer: your_data_layer

  postgres do
    table "tweet_hashtags"
    repo MyApp.Repo
  end

  relationships do
    belongs_to :tweet, MyApp.Tweet, primary_key?: true, allow_nil?: false
    belongs_to :hashtag, MyApp.Hashtag, primary_key?: true, allow_nil?: false
  end

  actions do
    defaults [:read, :destroy, create: :*, update: :*]
  end
end

It is convention to name this resource <source_resource_name><destination_resource_name> however this is not required. The attributes on the join resource must match the source_attribute_on_join_resource and destination_attribute_on_join_resource options on the many_to_many relationship. The relationships on the join resource are standard belongs_to relationships, and can be configured as such. In this case, we have specified that the :tweet_id and :hashtag_id attributes form the primary key for the join resource, and that they cannot be nil.

Now that we have a resource with the proper attributes, Ash will use this automatically under the hood when performing relationship operations like filtering and loading.

See the docs for more: d:Ash.Resource.Dsl.relationships.many_to_many

Loading related data

There are two ways to load relationships:

in the query using Ash.Query.load/2
directly on records using Ash.load/3

On records

Given a single record or a set of records, it is possible to load their relationships by calling the load function on the record's parent domain. For example:

# user = %User{...}
Ash.load(user, :tweets)

# users = [%User{...}, %User{...}, ....]
Ash.load(users, :tweets)

This will fetch the tweets for each user, and set them in the corresponding tweets key.

%User{
  ...
  tweets: [
    %Tweet{...},
    %Tweet{...},
    ...
  ]
}

See Ash.load/3 for more information.

In the query

The following will return a list of users with their tweets loaded identically to the previous example:

User
|> Ash.Query.load(:tweets)
|> Ash.read()

At present, loading relationships in the query is fundamentally the same as loading on records. Eventually, data layers will be able to optimize these loads (potentially including them as joins in the main query).

See Ash.Query.load/2 for more information.

More complex data loading

Multiple relationships can be loaded at once, i.e

Ash.load(users, [:tweets, :followers])

Nested relationships can be loaded:

Ash.load(users, followers: [:tweets, :followers])

The queries used for loading can be customized by providing a query as the value.

followers = Ash.Query.sort(User, follower_count: :asc)

Ash.load(users, followers: followers)

Nested loads will be included in the parent load.

followers =
  User
  |> Ash.Query.sort(follower_count: :asc)
  |> Ash.Query.load(:followers)

# Will load followers and followers of those followers
Ash.load(users, followers: followers)

no_attributes? true

This is really useful when creating customized relationships that aren't joined with simple attribute matches. For example:

has_many :higher_priority_tickets, __MODULE__ do
  no_attributes? true
  # parent/1 in this case puts the expression on this current resource
  # so this is "tickets with priority higher than this ticket"
  filter expr(priority > parent(priority))
end

This can also be useful when combined with schema-based multitenancy. Specifically, if you have a tenant resource like Organization, you can use no_attributes? to do things like has_many :employees, Employee, no_attributes?: true, which lets you avoid having an unnecessary organization_id field on Employee. The same works in reverse: has_one :organization, Organization, no_attributes?: true allows relating the employee to their organization.

You can also use no_attributes? true with attribute-based multitenancy in the same situation described above, to avoid an unnecessary second filter. If both resources have attribute multitenancy configured, they will already be filtered by organization_id by virtue of having set the tenant.

Caveats for using no_attributes?

You can still manage relationships from one to the other, but "relate" and "unrelate" will have no effect, because there are no fields to change.
Loading the relationship on a list of resources will not behave as expected in all circumstances involving multitenancy. For example, if you get a list of Organization and then try to load employees, you would need to set a single tenant on the load query, meaning you'll get all organizations back with the set of employees from one tenant. This could eventually be solved, but for now it is considered an edge case.

Manual Relationships

Manual relationships allow you to express complex or non-typical relationships between resources in a standard way. Individual data layers may interact with manual relationships in their own way, so see their corresponding guides. In general, you should try to use manual relationships sparingly, as you can do a lot with filters on relationships, and the no_attributes? flag.

Example

In our Helpdesk example, we'd like to have a way to find tickets

In the Representative resource, define a has_many relationship as manual and point to the module where it will be implemented.

relationships do
  has_many :tickets_above_threshold, Helpdesk.Support.Ticket do
    manual Helpdesk.Support.Ticket.Relationships.TicketsAboveThreshold
  end
end

Using Ash to get the destination records is ideal, so you can authorize access like normal but if you need to use a raw ecto query here, you can. As long as you return the right structure.

The TicketsAboveThreshold module is implemented as follows.

defmodule Helpdesk.Support.Ticket.Relationships.TicketsAboveThreshold do
  use Ash.Resource.ManualRelationship
  require Ash.Query

  def load(records, _opts, %{query: query} = context) do
    # Use existing records to limit results
    rep_ids = Enum.map(records, & &1.id)

    {:ok,
     query
     |> Ash.Query.filter(representative_id in ^rep_ids)
     |> Ash.Query.filter(priority > representative.priority_threshold)
     |> Ash.read!(Ash.Context.to_opts(context))
     # Return the items grouped by the primary key of the source, i.e representative.id => [...tickets above threshold]
     |> Enum.group_by(& &1.representative_id)}
  end
end

Reusing the Query

Since you likely want to support things like filtering your relationship when being loaded, you will want to make sure that you use the query being provided. However, depending on how you're loading the relationship, you may need to do things like fetch extra records. To do this, you might do things like

def load(records, _opts, %{query: query, ..}) do
  # unset some fields
  fetch_query = Ash.Query.unset(query, [:limit, :offset])

  # or, to be more safe/explicit, you might make a new query, explicitly setting only a few fields
  fetch_query = query.resource |> Ash.Query.filter(^query.filter) |> Ash.Query.sort(query.sort)

  ...
end

Query when loading with strict?: true

When using Ash.Query.load or Ash.load with the strict?: true option, the query that is provided to the load callback might be configured with a select-statement that doesn't load the attributes you want to group matching results by. If your codebase utilizes the strict loading functionality, it is therefore recommended to use Ash.Query.ensure_selected on the query to ensure the required attributes are indeed fetched.

# Here only :id & :priority is set, which will then configure the relationship query to only
# select those attributes
{:ok, rep} = Ash.load(representative, [tickets_above_threshold: [:id, :priority]], strict?: true)

defmodule Helpdesk.Support.Ticket.Relationships.TicketsAboveThreshold do
  use Ash.Resource.ManualRelationship
  require Ash.Query

  def load(records, _opts, %{query: query, actor: actor, authorize?: authorize?}) do
    rep_ids = Enum.map(records, & &1.id)

    {:ok,
     query
     # If this isn't added, representative_id would be set to %Ash.NotLoaded, causing the
     # Enum.group_by call below to fail mapping results to the correct records.
     |> Ash.Query.ensure_selected([:representative_id])
     |> Ash.Query.filter(representative_id in ^rep_ids)
     |> Ash.Query.filter(priority > representative.priority_threshold)
     |> Helpdesk.Support.read!(actor: actor, authorize?: authorize?)
     |> Enum.group_by(& &1.representative_id)}
  end
end

Fetching the records and then applying a query

Lets say the records come from some totally unrelated source, or you can't just modify the query to fetch the records you need. You can fetch the records you need and then apply the query to them in memory.

def load(records, _opts, %{query: query, ..}) do
  # fetch the data from the other source, which is capable of sorting
  data = get_other_data(data, query.sort)

  query
  # unset the sort since we already applied that
  |> Ash.Query.unset([:sort])
  # apply the query in memory (filtering, distinct, limit, offset)
  |> Ash.Query.apply_to(data)
end

Managing Relationships

Ash provides two primary approaches for managing related data, each suited to different scenarios:

Using change manage_relationship/3 in actions - When input comes from action arguments
Using Ash.Changeset.manage_relationship/4 directly - When building values programmatically in custom changes

When to Use Which Approach

Use change manage_relationship/3 when:

Input comes from action arguments (API endpoints, form submissions)
You want portable logic across different interfaces (GraphQL, JSON API)
You need standard CRUD operations on relationships
The relationship management logic is straightforward

Use Ash.Changeset.manage_relationship/4 when:

Building relationship data programmatically in custom changes
You need complex logic or data transformation before managing relationships
Conditional relationship management based on changeset state
Integration with external APIs or complex business rules

Order of operations

In destroy actions, relationships are managed after the main action is performed. This means if you're using manage_relationship to remove related records in a destroy action, and your database has foreign key constraints with "no action" or "restrict" settings, you may encounter constraint violations because Ash tries to destroy the primary resource first.

To work around this, you can:

Use the cascade_destroy builtin change instead of manage_relationship
Configure your database constraints to be deferred
Use different constraint settings that allow the operation order

Using change manage_relationship/3 in Actions

This is the most common approach for managing relationships through action arguments:

actions do
  update :update do
    argument :add_comment, :map do
      allow_nil? false
    end

    argument :tags, {:array, :uuid} do
      allow_nil? false
    end

    # First argument is the name of the action argument to use
    # Second argument is the relationship to be managed
    # Third argument is options. For more, see `Ash.Changeset.manage_relationship/4`.
    change manage_relationship(:add_comment, :comments, type: :create)

    # Second argument can be omitted when argument name matches relationship name
    change manage_relationship(:tags, type: :append_and_remove)
  end
end

With this setup, you can use the arguments in action input:

post
|> Ash.Changeset.for_update(:update, %{
  tags: [tag1.id, tag2.id],
  add_comment: %{text: "comment text"}
})
|> Ash.update!()

Common Patterns with Actions

Creating with related data:

create :create_with_author do
  argument :author, :map, allow_nil?: false
  change manage_relationship(:author, type: :create)
end

# Usage
Post
|> Ash.Changeset.for_create(:create_with_author, %{
  title: "My Post",
  author: %{name: "John Doe", email: "john@example.com"}
})
|> Ash.create!()

Managing many-to-many relationships:

update :manage_categories do
  argument :category_names, {:array, :string}

  change manage_relationship(:category_names, :categories,
    type: :append_and_remove,
    value_is_key: :name,
    on_lookup: :relate,
    on_no_match: :create
  )
end

Different argument and relationship names:

update :assign_reviewer do
  argument :reviewer_id, :uuid
  change manage_relationship(:reviewer_id, :reviewer, type: :append_and_remove)
end

Using Ash.Changeset.manage_relationship/4 in Custom Changes

For more complex scenarios, you can use Ash.Changeset.manage_relationship/4 directly in custom changes:

defmodule MyApp.Changes.AssignProjectMembers do
  use Ash.Resource.Change

  def change(changeset, _opts, context) do
    # Get the current user from context
    current_user = context.actor

    # Build relationship data based on business logic
    members = determine_project_members(changeset, current_user)

    # Manage the relationship directly
    Ash.Changeset.manage_relationship(
      changeset,
      :members,
      members,
      type: :append_and_remove,
      authorize?: true
    )
  end

  defp determine_project_members(changeset, current_user) do
    # Complex logic to determine who should be project members
    # based on changeset data and business rules
    # ...
  end
end

Conditional relationship management:

defmodule MyApp.Changes.ConditionalTagging do
  use Ash.Resource.Change

  def change(changeset, _opts, _context) do
    # Only manage tags if certain conditions are met
    if should_auto_tag?(changeset) do
      tags = generate_auto_tags(changeset)

      Ash.Changeset.manage_relationship(
        changeset,
        :tags,
        tags,
        type: :append,
        on_no_match: :create
      )
    else
      changeset
    end
  end
end

Data transformation before relationship management:

defmodule MyApp.Changes.ProcessOrderItems do
  use Ash.Resource.Change

  def change(changeset, _opts, _context) do
    case Ash.Changeset.fetch_argument(changeset, :raw_items) do
      {:ok, raw_items} ->
        # Transform and validate the raw item data
        processed_items =
          raw_items
          |> validate_items()
          |> calculate_pricing()
          |> apply_discounts()

        Ash.Changeset.manage_relationship(
          changeset,
          :items,
          processed_items,
          type: :direct_control
        )

      :error ->
        changeset
    end
  end
end

Management Types and Options

Ash provides several built-in management types that configure common relationship management patterns:

Management Types

:append - Add new related records, ignore existing ones

change manage_relationship(:tags, type: :append)
# Equivalent to:
# on_lookup: :relate, on_no_match: :error, on_match: :ignore, on_missing: :ignore

:append_and_remove - Add new related records, remove missing ones

change manage_relationship(:tags, type: :append_and_remove)
# Equivalent to:
# on_lookup: :relate, on_no_match: :error, on_match: :ignore, on_missing: :unrelate

:remove - Remove specified related records

change manage_relationship(:tags, type: :remove)
# Equivalent to:
# on_no_match: :error, on_match: :unrelate, on_missing: :ignore

:direct_control - Full CRUD control over the related records

change manage_relationship(:comments, type: :direct_control)
# Equivalent to:
# on_lookup: :ignore, on_no_match: :create, on_match: :update, on_missing: :destroy

:create - Only create new related records

change manage_relationship(:items, type: :create)
# Equivalent to:
# on_no_match: :create, on_match: :ignore

Key Options

on_lookup - How to handle records that might exist elsewhere:

:ignore - Don't look up existing records
:relate - Look up and relate existing records
{:relate, :action_name} - Use specific action for relating

on_no_match - What to do when no matching record exists:

:ignore - Skip these inputs
:create - Create new records
{:create, :action_name} - Use specific create action
:error - Raise an error

on_match - What to do when a matching record is found:

:ignore - Leave the record as-is
:update - Update the existing record
{:update, :action_name} - Use specific update action
:unrelate - Remove the relationship
:error - Raise an error

on_missing - What to do with related records not in the input:

:ignore - Leave them as-is
:unrelate - Remove the relationship
:destroy - Delete the records
{:destroy, :action_name} - Use specific destroy action

Decision Flow

The following diagram shows how manage_relationship processes input records using these options:

flowchart TD
    A[manage_relationship input] --> B[Load existing relationships]

    B --> C[Does input exist in current relationships?]
    B --> L

    C -->|Yes - Found match| D[on_match behavior]
    C -->|No - No match found| E[on_lookup behavior]

    E -->|:ignore| F[on_no_match behavior]
    E -->|:relate| G[Query destination resource<br/>using input identities]

    G --> H[Found in lookup?]
    H -->|Yes| I[:relate - Add relationship]
    H -->|No| F

    D --> D1[:ignore - Leave as-is]
    D --> D2[:update - Update existing]
    D --> D3[:unrelate - Remove relationship]
    D --> D4[:error - Raise error]

    F --> F1[:ignore - Skip input]
    F --> F2[:create - Create new record]
    F --> F3[:error - Raise error]

    L[Existing related records not in input] --> J[on_missing behavior]

    J --> J1[:ignore - Leave as-is]
    J --> J2[:unrelate - Remove relationship]
    J --> J3[:destroy - Delete records]

    style A fill:#e1f5fe
    style D1 fill:#fff3e0
    style D2 fill:#e8f5e8
    style D3 fill:#fce4ec
    style D4 fill:#ffebee
    style F1 fill:#fff3e0
    style F2 fill:#e8f5e8
    style F3 fill:#ffebee
    style I fill:#e8f5e8
    style J1 fill:#fff3e0
    style J2 fill:#fce4ec
    style J3 fill:#ffcdd2

Advanced Options

value_is_key - Use a specific field as the key when providing simple values:

# Allow using category names instead of IDs
change manage_relationship(:category_names, :categories,
  value_is_key: :name,
  type: :append_and_remove
)

use_identities - Specify which identities to use for lookups:

change manage_relationship(:tags,
  type: :append_and_remove,
  use_identities: [:name, :_primary_key]
)

join_keys - For many-to-many relationships, specify join table parameters:

change manage_relationship(:categories,
  type: :append_and_remove,
  join_keys: [:priority, :added_by]
)

Relationship Type Considerations

belongs_to Relationships

When managing belongs_to relationships, you're typically setting a parent:

create :create_with_parent do
  argument :parent, :map
  change manage_relationship(:parent, type: :create)
end

# Or relating to existing parent
update :assign_parent do
  argument :parent_id, :uuid
  change manage_relationship(:parent_id, :parent, type: :append_and_remove)
end

has_one Relationships

For has_one relationships, you manage a single related record:

update :update_profile do
  argument :profile, :map
  change manage_relationship(:profile, type: :direct_control)
end

has_many Relationships

With has_many, you typically manage collections:

update :manage_comments do
  argument :comments, {:array, :map}
  change manage_relationship(:comments, type: :direct_control)
end

many_to_many Relationships

Many-to-many relationships often involve join table management:

update :update_post_tags do
  argument :tags, {:array, :map}

  change manage_relationship(:tags,
    type: :append_and_remove,
    join_keys: [:tagged_at, :tagged_by]
  )
end

Advanced Patterns

Multiple manage_relationship Calls

You can call manage_relationship multiple times, and they'll be processed in order:

update :complex_update do
  argument :add_tags, {:array, :string}
  argument :remove_tags, {:array, :string}

  change manage_relationship(:add_tags, :tags,
    type: :append,
    value_is_key: :name,
    meta: [order: 1]
  )

  change manage_relationship(:remove_tags, :tags,
    type: :remove,
    value_is_key: :name,
    meta: [order: 2]
  )
end

Argument Types and Value Handling

Map and List Inputs

When providing maps or lists of maps, you're providing input for actions on the destination resource:

# Maps become action input
argument :comment, :map
change manage_relationship(:comment, :comments, type: :create)

# Usage:
%{comment: %{text: "Great post!", rating: 5}}

Simple Value Inputs

You can also provide simple values using value_is_key:

argument :tag_names, {:array, :string}
change manage_relationship(:tag_names, :tags,
  type: :append_and_remove,
  value_is_key: :name,
  on_lookup: :relate,
  on_no_match: :create
)

# Usage:
%{tag_names: ["elixir", "phoenix", "ash"]}

Using Existing Records

You can also pass existing record structs directly:

# In a custom change
existing_tags = Ash.read!(Tag, actor: actor)
Ash.Changeset.manage_relationship(changeset, :tags, existing_tags, type: :append)

Authorization considerations

When you pass existing record structs directly to manage_relationship, Ash assumes that the actor is already authorized to read those records. This bypasses the normal authorization checks that would occur if you had provided IDs instead.

If you provide ids/maps, Ash will read the records and properly check authorization. Only pass existing record structs when you're certain the actor has appropriate read permissions for those records, or authorization is not relevant.

Integration with Tools

The explicit nature of relationship management options enables rich integrations:

AshPhoenix.Form - Automatically derives nested form structures
AshGraphQL - Generates complex input objects for mutations
AshJsonApi - Creates appropriate API endpoints for relationship management

This works because Ash can determine exactly what actions might be called and what input is needed based on your manage_relationship configuration.

For complete documentation of all available options, see Ash.Changeset.manage_relationship/4.

Sensitive Data

Public & Private Attributes

By default, attributes, calculations, aggregates and relationships are private (they are marked public?: false).
If you are working with Ash in code, reading a resource, for example using Ash.read/2, the public/private status of an attribute is not relevant.
However, when working with api extensions like AshGraphql and AshJsonApi, they will only include public fields in their interfaces. This helps avoid accidentally exposing data over "public" interfaces.

Public & Private Arguments

Public/private arguments work the same way as public/private fields, except that they default to public?: true.
This is because arguments to an action being used in a public interface would naturally be expected to be public. If an argument is marked as public?: false, it can only be set using one of the following methods:

Ash.Query.set_argument/3
Ash.Changeset.set_argument/3
By setting private_argument option when creating a changeset. For eg., Ash.Changeset.for_create(:create_with_private_argument, %{public_title: "title"}, private_arguments: %{private_name: "private"}

Sensitive Attributes

Using sensitive? true will cause an attribute, calculation or argument to show as "** Redacted **" when inspecting records.
In filter statements, any value used in the same expression as a sensitive field will also be redacted. For example, you might see: email == "** Redacted **" in a filter statement if email is marked as sensitive.

Show Sensitive Attributes

IMPORTANT WARNING: The following configuration should only ever be used in development mode!

To display sensitive attributes in their original form during development, use the following config.

config :ash, show_sensitive?: true

Field Policies

Field policies are a way to control the visibility of individual fields (except for relationships) as a part of authorization flow, for those using Ash.Policy.Authorizer.
If a field is not visible, it will be populated with %Ash.ForbiddenField{}, or will be not shown (or may show an error) in public interfaces. See the Policies guide for more.

Upgrade

Other Packages

Other packages have had a major version bump in addition to Ash core. While all packages have been changed to refer to domain instead of api, they did not receive a major version bump because there were no special breaking changes to account for when using that package. You will also need to factor in the following upgrade guides, if you use those packages.

AshPostgres
AshJsonApi
AshGraphql

Upgrading to 3.0

This section contains each breaking change, and the steps required to address it in your application

Dependency Changes

Ash.Flow

If you use Ash.Flow, include {:ash_flow, "~> 0.1.0"} in your application.

Picosat Elixir

In 2.0, Ash had a dependency on picosat_elixir. In 3.0, this is an optional dependency, to help folks handle certain compatibility issues. To upgrade, add {:picosat_elixir, "~> 0.2"} to your mix.exs.

Ash.Api is now Ash.Domain

The previous name was often confusing as this is an overloaded term for many. To that end, Ash.Api has been renamed to Ash.Domain, which better fits our usage and concepts.

What you'll need to change

To make this change you will need to do two things:

replace Ash.Api with Ash.Domain in your application
replace places where an :api option is passed to a function with the :domain option. For example, AshPhoenix.Form.for_create(..., api: MyApp.SomeApi) should now be AshPhoenix.Form.for_create(..., domain: MyApp.SomeDomain)
Update your application config to define ash_domains instead of ash_apis, eg. config :my_app, ash_domains: [MyApp.MyDomain]

DSL Changes

code_interface.define_for is now code_interface.domain. Additionally, it is set automatically if the domain option is specified on use Ash.Resource.

domain.execution.timeout used to default to 30 seconds, but now it defaults to :infinity. This is because a timeout requires copying memory across process boundaries, and is an unnecessary expense a vast majority of the time. We recommend putting timeouts on specific actions that may need them.

actions.create.reject, actions.update.reject and actions.destroy.reject have been removed. Blacklisting inputs makes it too easy to make mistakes. Instead, specify an explicit accept list.

relationships.belongs_to.attribute_writable? no longer makes the underlying attribute both public and writable. It defaults to the value of writable? on the relationship (which itself defaults to true), and only controls the generated attributes writable? true property. So now, by default, it will be true, which is safe when coupled with changes to the default_accept, discussed below. Generally, this means you should be safe to remove any occurrences of attribute_writable? true.

relationships.belongs_to.attribute_public? has been added, which controls the underlying attribute's public? value. This, similar to attribute_writable? defaults to the public? attribute of the relationship.

resource.simple_notifiers has been removed, in favor of specifying non-DSL notifiers in the simple_notifiers option to use Ash.Resource.

resource.actions.read.filter can now be specified multiple times. Multiple filters will be combined with and.

Ash.Registry has been removed

Ash.Registry is no longer needed. Place each resource in the domain instead.

resources do
  resource Resource1
  resource Resource2
end

Expression changes

When calling a calculation with arguments, this is done via passing a keyword list to the calculation, for example: full_name(separator: ""). In 2.0, keyword lists were not evaluated as part of the expression in the same way as other values, meaning two things:

You did not have to pin usage of template functions, i.e full_name(separator: arg(:separator)). Now, you will need to do so: full_name(separator: ^arg(:separator))

You had to use expr to pass an expression to a calculation argument (this only works if allow_expr? true is configured on the calculation argument). For example: full_name(separator: expr(sep_1 <> sep_2)) would now be full_name(separator: sep_1 <> sep_2)

If you do not have any expression calculations that accept arguments, you likely need to do nothing. To make these changes, you will need to look at each place you build an expression that you may be calling a calculation w/ arguments, i.e Ash.Query.filter, and the expression callback in Ash.Calculation, and see if they must be modified as described above.

Module/function changes

Ash.Policy.FilterCheck and Ash.Policy.FilterCheckWithContext are combined

Ash.Policy.FilterCheck and Ash.Policy.FilterCheckWithContext have been combined into Ash.Policy.FilterCheck. If you have any usages of FilterCheckWithContext, you'll need to change that to FilterCheck. If you have usages of FilterCheck, you will need to add the context arguments to the callbacks. Compiler warnings will show you what callbacks mismatch.

Ash.Filter

Ash.Filter.parse/5 is now Ash.Filter.parse/3. Ash.Filter.parse_input/5 is now Ash.Filter.parse_input/2 The third and fourth optional arguments are unnecessary and were previously ignored, and the fifth argument is not necessary for parse_input.

Ash.Filter.used_aggregates/3 no longer accepts :all as a relationship path, instead using :*. Its very unlikely that this is used in your application.

Ash.Filter.TemplateHelpers

Tools for templating expressions were previously in Ash.Filter.TemplateHelpers. This often led to confusion because it was a hard to remember module name, and didn't really make sense to be separate from the rest of our utilities. Now, all the functions/macros you need for expressions are in Ash.Expr. This means that in any given file where you want to work with expressions, you only need to do import Ash.Expr. Additionally, this import Ash.Expr has been added to changes, preparations, validations and calculations automatically.

Ash.CiString

Ash.CiString.new(nil) now returns nil instead of %Ash.CiString{value: nil}

Ash.Resource.Validation

validate/2 is now validate/3, with the third argument being the context of the validation.

Ash.Query.Calculation

The function signature of Ash.Query.Calculation.new has been changed. We use an options list over optional arguments, and now require constraints to be provided. You will need to adjust your calls to this function.

Ash.Calculation

This module has been renamed to Ash.Resource.Calculation. You will need to rename your references to it.

Ash.Query

Ash.Query.to_query has been removed. Use Ash.Query.new instead.

Ash.Query.expr has been removed. Use Ash.Expr.expr instead.

Aggregates

first and list aggregates have a new option called include_nil?, which defaults to false. You may need to add include_nil?: true to your resource aggregates if you wish to retain the old behavior.

New format for sorting on calculations with arguments

The format for sorting on calculations that take input has been swapped. Previously, you would use sort(calculation: {:desc, %{arg: :value}}), but for the sake of consistency, you now use sort(calculation: {%{arg: :value}, :desc}).

Ash.Changeset

Ash.Changeset.new/2 has been removed. Ash.Changeset.new/1 is still available for creating a new changeset, but attributes and arguments should, with few exceptions, be passed to the relevant Ash.Changeset.for_<action_type> functions, not to Ash.Changeset.new/2. Removing the second argument helps clarify the purpose of Ash.Changeset.new/1.

Ash.Changeset.after_transaction/2 can no longer be called from within other lifecycle hooks. We need to know whether or not an after action hook, before we start processing any hooks.

Ash.Changeset.manage_relationship/4 no longer uses :all to signal that all changes will be sent to the join relationship. Instead, use :*.

Ash.Changeset.filter now accepts expressions. The value of the filter is no longer a simple equality map, but rather a regular Ash expression. We add to it on successive calls to Ash.Changeset.filter. Additionally, this value is stored in changeset.filter instead of changeset.filters.

Ash.Policy.FilterCheckWithContext

Ash.Policy.FilterCheck and Ash.Policy.FilterCheckWithContext have been combined. The name is Ash.Policy.FilterCheck, but the callbacks take the extra arguments present in Ash.Policy.FilterCheckWithContext.

Builtin Changes & Preparations

The functions provided to after_action/1, after_transaction/1, before_transaction/1 and before_action/1 must all now take an additional argument, which is the change context.

For example,

change after_action(fn changeset, result -> ... end)

is now

change after_action(fn changeset, result, context -> ... end)

This is true for both preparations and changes.

Expressions

Previously, in expressions, you could say expr(ref(^some_atom)). This is a tool for building dynamic references, but it was an exception to the standard pattern of prefixing "external" things in an expression, i.e arg with ^. Now, you must do the same with ref/1 and ref/2. You will need to search for ref( in your application, and ensure that if it is inside of an expression you have prefixed it with ^. The original example becomes: expr(^ref(some_atom)).

Exception changes

Ash exceptions have been simplified and are now backed by Splode

Usage of def_ash_error/2 will show you what to change in its warnings.

Instead of combining def_ash_error with defimpl Ash.ErrorKind, you create a custom error like so:

defmodule MyCustomError do
  use Splode.Error, class: :invalid, fields: [:foo, :bar]

  def message(error) do
    "Message: #{error.foo} - #{error.bar}"
  end
end

Ash exception changes

When sorting or filtering, if a field is not found, an Ash.Query.Error.NoSuchField is used, where it would have previously been an Ash.Query.Error.NoSuchAttribute. This was wrong as sometimes the field reference was not an attribute. Places that would previously return Ash.Query.Error.NoSuchAttributeOrRelationship now return Ash.Query.Error.NoSuchField as well.

Additionally, the following exceptions have had keys remapped:

NoSuchAttribute: name -> attribute NoSuchRelationship: name -> relationship NoSuchFunction: name -> function NoSuchOperator: name -> operator

Significant Changes

Ash.set_* functions have been removed

In 2.0, a set of features allowed storing the actor, tenant and context in the process dictionary. There were fundamental issues with this pattern that manifested in subtle bugs. We suggest making this change before you upgrade, as this change can be made and verified without upgrading to 3.0.

What you'll need to change

You need to manually thread through your tenant, actor, and context values wherever you were using Ash.set_*. For example:

Ash.set_actor(current_user)
Ash.set_tenant(current_tenant)

Ash.Changeset.for_create!(..)
Ash.Query.for_read(..)

would become

Ash.Changeset.for_create!(.., tenant: current_tenant, actor: current_user)
Ash.Query.for_read(.., tenant: current_tenant, actor: current_user)

The Domain of a resource must now be known when constructing a changeset, query or action input

In order to honor rules on the Domain module about authorization and timeouts, we have to know the Domain when building the changeset.

What you'll need to change

Embedded Resources

The domain for the calls to embedded resources is gotten from the parent changeset. No need to change them at all. a domain constraint has been added in case you wish to make a given embedded resource use a specific domain always.

For example:

attribute :bio, MyApp.Bio do
  constraints domain: MyApp.SomeDomain
end

Single Domain resources

While it is possible for resources to be used with multiple domains, it almost never happens in practice. Any resources that are only used from a single domain only (not including embedded resources) should be modified to have a domain option specified in their call to use Ash.Resource. For example:

use Ash.Resource,
  domain: MyApp.MyDomain

Using Ash.* to interact with your resources

Calling functions on the domain has been deprecated. You must now use the functions defined in the Ash module to interact with your resources. They are the same as what was previously available in your domain module. For example:

MyDomain1.create!(changeset)
MyDomain2.read!(query)
MyDomain3.calculate!(...)

can now be written as

Ash.create!(changeset)
Ash.read!(query)
Ash.calculate!(query)

This makes refactoring resources easier, as you no longer need to change the call site, it remains the same regardless of what Domain a resource is in.

Multi Domain resources

For these, you will need to include the domain option when you construct a changeset.

For example:

MyResource
|> Ash.Changeset.for_create(:create, input, domain: MyApp.MyDomain)

Actions no longer default to accepting all public writable attributes

For more context, see the original discussion: https://github.com/ash-project/ash/issues/512

In 2.0, all public, writable attributes were accepted by each action by default. This made it very easy to accidentally expose writing to an attribute in an action where that was not the intent. Additionally, new attributes added were automatically writable across a wide array of actions, which was error prone for the same reason.

In 2.0, as well as 3.0, there is an option called default_accept, which modifies all actions that do not have an accept list. In 2.0, the default value for default_accept was "all public, writable attributes". In 3.0, the default value for default_accept is []. This encourages a pattern of explicitly listing inputs to actions, and is safer and less error prone.

What you'll need to change

For those who want to upgrade, you would use the new :* option to default_accept (also usable in an action's accept option) to accept all public attributes. Go to each resource and, inside the actions block, add:

actions do
  default_accept :*
  ...
end

Then mark the attributes and relationships you want to accept as public?: true (see this section for more information on this change).

For those who want to be more explicit, or after your upgrade has complete if you wish to refactor existing resources and actions, the general best path forward is to copy the default_accept into each action (or put it in a module attribute and reference it) as the accept option. This way when a new action is added, it does not "inherit" some list of accepted attributes.

:* private attributes can now be accepted

In 2.0, accepting a private attribute as a change required adding an argument with the same name, and using change set_attribute(...). Now that we require explicit accept lists, you can place private attributes in that list, which will allow them to be written to (but not read back).

:* includes belongs_to attributes!

The change to explicit accepts also included a change that defaults belongs_to attributes to writable?: true and public?: false. You may want to add attribute_writable?: false to your belongs_to relationships if you are adding default_accept :* and don't currently have attribute_writable?: true on them currently.

Default actions :create and :update can now have an accept list

For example:

defaults [:read, :destroy, create: :*, update: :*]

Default read actions are now paginatable

In 2.0, if you have :read in your default actions list, it would generate an action like this:

read :read do
  primary? true
end

Now, it generates an action like this:

read :read do
  primary? true
  pagination [keyset?: true, offset?: true, countable: true, required?: false]
end

What you will need to change

For most cases, this won't affect you. However, if you are using AshGraphql, and have any queries connected to a default :read action, it will default to making those queries paginatable with keyset pagination. To keep the old behavior, you will need to add paginate_with nil to the query, for example:

graphql do
  queries do
    list :list_things, :read, paginate_with: nil
  end
end

Before action and before transaction hooks order has been reversed

In Ash 2.0, before_action and before_transaction hooks that were added to a changeset were prepended to the list of hooks by default. These hooks were then run in order. What this meant is that, given an action like the following:

create :foo do
  change before_action(fn changeset, _context ->
    IO.puts("first")
    changeset
  end)

  change before_action(fn changeset, _context ->
    IO.puts("second")
    changeset
  end)
end

You would see second printed before first.

What you'll need to change

In many cases, this won't matter to you. However, if you have a situation where the order of your before action/transaction hooks matters, you can do one of two things:

reorder the changes that add those before action/transaction hooks
use the :prepend option to Ash.Changeset.before_action/2 and Ash.Changeset.before_transaction/2 to explicitly prepend the hook to the list of hooks

Context in changes, preparations, validations, calculations are now structs

To help make it clear what keys are available in the context provided to callbacks on these modules, they have been adjusted to provide a struct instead of a map. This helps avoid potential ambiguity, and acts as documentation.

What you'll need to change

If you are using something like Keyword.new(context) to generate options to pass into an action, change that to Ash.Context.to_opts(context).

Calculation arguments are now in context.arguments

Per the above change, we have specified the values available in the context of a calculation, with Ash.Resource.Calculation.Context. In Ash 2.0, context was merged with arguments, which was problematic in various ways. Now, arguments are in context.arguments.

What you'll need to change

You will need to update your module-backed calculations to account for this.

def calculate(records, _opts, context) do
  Enum.map(records, fn record ->
    record.first_name <> context.delimiter <> record.last_name
  end)
end

would need to be adjusted to access arguments in the context:

def calculate(records, _opts, %{arguments: arguments}) do
  Enum.map(records, fn record ->
    record.first_name <> arguments.delimiter <> record.last_name
  end)
end

private?: true -> public?: true

There is no longer a private? option for attributes, relationships, calculations and aggregates. Instead of attributes defaulting to private?: false, they now default to public?: false. It was too easy to add an attribute and not realize that you had exposed it over your api.

What you'll need to change

If you are using api extensions (i.e AshGraphql and AshJsonApi), you will need to go to your resources and "invert" the definitions. i.e remove private?: true and add public?: true to every other attribute, relationship and calculation. Don't forget the relationships and calculations!

Embedded resources too!

The above includes embedded resources as well! Don't forget to make sure that all fields on your embedded resources are also marked as public?: true (if applicable). The goal here is to have a clear visual indicator of what in your application can be shown publicly.

Anonymous calculations now operate on a list, just like module calculations

Previously, anonymous function calculations were special cased to operate on a single record. For consistency, these anonymous functions now take the list of records.

What you'll need to change

Update any anonymous function calculations to take and return a list, for example:

calculate :full_name, :string, fn record, _context ->
  record.first_name <> " " <> record.last_name
end

would become

calculate :full_name, :string, fn records, _context ->
  # note, you can also return `{:ok, list}` or `{:error, error}`
  Enum.map(records, fn record ->
    record.first_name <> " " <> record.last_name
  end)
end

Calculation loads do not select all related fields by default

In 2.0 relationship loads from the load/3 callback in a calculation will select all fields of that relationship and make them available to the calculation.

For example, the following calculation load/3 callback expresses a dependency on all fields of the relationship :relationship.

def load(_, _, _) do
  [:relationship]
end

What you'll need to change

Refactor

In 3.0, relationship dependencies alone will only make the related primary keys available. You now need to select explicit fields that you want to use in your calculation, for example:

def load(_, _, _) do
  [relationship: [:field1, :field2]]
end

Keep the old behavior

Each calculation can still opt into the old behavior by adding the callback strict_loads/0 and returning false.

def load(_, _, _) do
  [:relationship]
end

def strict_loads, do: false

Calculations do not have a select/3 callback any more

In 2.0 calculations had a select/3 callback, but load/3 is now a superset of select/3 and so the former is no longer needed.

What you'll need to change

If you have a select/3 callback in your calculations, you will need to remove the select/3 callback. You must then add those fields to the load/3 callback.

For example:

def select(_, _, _), do: [:some_attribute]
def load(_, _, _), do: [:some_calculation, some_relationship: [:some_field1, :some_field2]]

can now be written more simply as:

def load(_, _, _), do: [:some_attribute, :some_calculation, some_relationship: [:some_field1, :some_field2]]

Embedded resources no longer have autogenerated_id

A private primary key called autogenerated_id was added to embedded resources if no primary key was added manually.

This should have no real effect on your application, except for the fact that your embedded attributes will have autogenerated_id in the database which won't be reflected by an attribute any more. If it is updated, then the autogenerated_id field will go away.

This is listed as a breaking change in case someone is depending on this feature, but that should be very uncommon/unlikely.

PubSub notifier no longer publishes events for previous values by default

Previously, the Ash notifier would publish a message containing both the old and new values for changing attributes. Typically, we use things like IDs in notification topics, that do not change, so for most this will not have an impact.

If you wish to send a notification for the old value and the new value, then an action cannot be done atomically. Bulk actions must update each record in turn, and atomic updates can't be leveraged.

If you're comfortable with the performance implications, you can restore the previous behavior by adding previous_values?: true to your publications in your pub_sub notifier

publish :update, ["user:updated", :email], previous_values?: true

Custom checks and notifiers will not have access to the original data by default

In your notifiers and policy checks, when you get a changeset you currently have access to the data field, which is the original record prior to being updated or destroyed. However, this is not compatible with atomic/bulk updates/destroys, where we may be given a query and told to destroy it. In those cases, changeset.data will be %Ash.Changeset.OriginalDataNotAvailable{}. When you write a custom check or a custom notifier, if you need access to the original data, you must add the following function:

# in custom checks
def requires_original_data?(_authorizer, _opts), do: true

# in notifiers
def requires_original_data?(_resource, _action), do: true

Keep in mind, this will prevent the usage of these checks/notifiers with atomic actions.

Domain.authorization.authorize now defaults to :by_default

Previously, the default was :when_requested. This meant that, unless you said actor: some_actor or authorize?: true, authorization was skipped. This has the obvious drawback of making it easy to accidentally bypass authorization unintentionally. In 3.0, this now defaults to :by_default.

What you'll need to change

Keep old behavior

To avoid making a significant refactor, and to keep your current behavior, you can go to your domain and set the configuration below. Otherwise skip to the refactor steps below. We advise that you take this route to start, but we highly suggest that you change your domains to authorize :by_default in the future. authorize :when_requested will not be deprecated, so there is no time constraint.

authorization do
  authorize :when_requested
end

Refactor

For each domain that has the old configuration, after setting it to the new config, you'll need to revisit each call to that domain that doesn't set an actor or the authorize? option, and add authorize?: false.

This may be a good time to do the refactor from YourDomain.func to Ash.func, if you want to. See the section about domains being required when building changesets.

require_atomic? defaults to true

On :update actions, and :destroy actions, they now default to require_atomic? true. This means that the following things will cause errors when attempting to run the action:

changes or validations exist that do not have the atomic callback. This includes anonymous function changes/validations.
attributes are being changed that do not support atomic updates. This most notably includes (for now) embedded resources.
the action has a manual implementation
the action has applicable notifiers that require the original data.

Updates and destroys that can be made fully atomic are always safe to do concurrently, and as such we now require that actions meet this criteria, or that it is explicitly stated that they do not have to. See the update actions guide for more.

Upgrade config

You can set the following configuration, which will be removed in Ash 3.1. This configuration will retain the 2.0 default behavior of require_atomic? defaulting to false. You can then safely do the rest of the upgrade. Then, you can perform this one change after confirming that your system works as expected.

config :ash, :require_atomic_by_default?, false

What you'll need to change

The vast majority of cases will be caught by warnings emitted at compile time.

Anonymous function changes

Anonymous function changes can never be made atomic, because we don't know what they contain. You will either need to transfer it to a module change and then follow the next section, or set require_atomic? false

Module changes

If you have a module change, you can make it atomic by defining the atomic/3 callback. This callback can replace the change/3 callback, but it is very important to keep in mind that later changes will no longer have access to the value. For example, if you have

def change(changeset, _, _) do
  # this is not concurrency safe
  Ash.Changeset.change_attribute(changeset, :value, changeset.data.value + 1)
end

If you have a subsequent change that does something like Ash.Changeset.get_attribute(changeset, :value) it will get the new value (i.e old value + 1). With atomics, Ash.Changeset.get_attribute(changeset, :value) would return the old value. This is because atomics are scheduling an update that happens when call the data layer. For example:

def atomic(changeset, _, _) do
  {:atomic, %{value: expr(value + 1)}}
end

This should not typically matter unless you have complex actions w/ multiple changes where subsequent changes need to know the results of previous steps. In those cases, if you can't make them all atomic, then its best just not to worry about it and set require_atomic? false

Non-atomic castable types

If you are using change atomic_update/2 or Ash.Changeset.atomic_update/2 or Ash.Changeset.atomic_update/3, and the type does not support atomic updates, you will get an error unless you do one of the following:

for change atomic_update/2 add the cast_atomic?: false option.
for Ash.Changeset.atomic_update, pass the value as {:atomic, expr}, i.e Ash.Changeset.atomic_update(changeset, :value, {:atomic, expr(value + 1)})

For builtin types, the above applies to :union, :map, :keyword, embedded types. It also applies to :string, but only if the match? constraint is present.

Ash.Error.Invalid.NoSuchInput errors on unknown action inputs

In 2.0, inputs to actions that don't match an accepted attribute or argument were silently ignored. This made it very easy to make certain kinds of mistakes, like assuming that an input is being used by an action when it actually is not. Now, unknown action inputs will cause an Ash.Error.Invalid.NoSuchInput.

What you'll need to change

If you have action calls that are erroneously passing in extra values, you will need to do remove them.

A logic error was fixed in this behavior for embedded resources. If you are using embedded resources in {:array, _} types, and are relying on including the primary key of that embedded resource to match records up for updating/destroy behavior, you will need to make sure that you do one of the following

add the writable?: true flag to the uuid of the embedded resource (probably what you want)
modify the actions to accept an id argument and set the argument to the provided value

%Ash.NotLoaded{} for attributes

In 2.0, attributes that were not selected were replaced with nil values. This could lead to confusion when dealing with records that didn't have all attributes selected. If you passed these records to a function it might see that an attribute is nil when actually it just wasn't selected. To find out if it was selected, you could look into record.__metadata__.selected, but you'd have to know to do that. To alleviate these issues, attributes that are not selected are now filled in with %Ash.NotLoaded{}, just like calculations and aggregates.

What you'll need to change

If you have logic that was looking at attribute values that may not be selected, you may have been accidentally working with non selected values. For example:

if record.attribute do
  handle_present_attribute(...)
else
  # unselected attributes would have ended up in this branch
  handle_not_present_attribute(...)
end

Now, if it is possible for that attribute to have not been selected, you'll want to do something like this instead:

case record.attribute do
  %Ash.NotLoaded{} ->
    handle_not_selected(...)
  nil ->
    handle_not_present_attribute(...)
  value ->
    handle_present_attribute(...)
end

Calculations do not reuse values by default

When loading data in 2.0 the option reselect_all? defaulted to false. What this would mean is that existing values for attributes would be reused, instead of visiting the data layer, by default. This can be an extremely valuable piece of behavior, but defaulting to it often means accidentally using data as a cache that you did not intent to use as a cache. Take the following example:

user = %User{first_name: "fred", last_name: "weasley"}

Ash.update!(user, first_name: "george")

user |> Ash.load!(:full_name)
# in 2.0 -> fred weasley
# in 3.0 -> george weasley

To opt into the old behavior, which we recommend doing on a case-by-case basis, you can pass reuse_values?: true. For example:

user |> Ash.load!(:full_name, reuse_values?: true)

Resources are not interchangeable with Ash.Type anymore

In 2.0 it was possible to pass an Ash resource in all places where some instance of Ash.Type was supported. In 3.0 resources (except for embedded resources) don't implement the Ash.Type behaviour anymore.

What you'll need to change

If you were using a resource in one of the places that accept an Ash.Type (arguments, calculation return values or fields of a union) you have to refactor your code to use the :struct type together with an instance_of constraint

calculation :random_post, :struct do
  constraints instance_of: Post
  calculate Calculations.RandomPost
end

What is Ash?

Ash is an opinionated, declarative application framework that brings the batteries-included experience to Elixir. It shines when building web apps, APIs and services, but can be used for any kind of Elixir application. It integrates with the best that the Elixir ecoystem has to offer, often used with Phoenix and PostgreSQL, slotting directly into a standard Elixir codebase. Ash is built for velocity at day 1, but also for maintainability at year 5, a place where many frameworks and tools leave you high and dry.

Through its declarative extensibility, Ash delivers more than you'd expect: Powerful APIs with filtering/sorting/pagination/calculations/aggregations, pub/sub, authorization, rich introspection, GraphQL... It's what empowers this solo developer to build an ambitious ERP!

— Frank Dugan III, System Specialist, SunnyCor Inc.

At its heart, Ash is a framework for modeling your application's domain through Resources and their Actions. These are the fundamental abstractions that everything else builds upon.

Why Ash?

If you've ever built software professionally, you've almost certainly experienced one or more of the following:

The problem:

Repetitive work - The same business logic scattered across our application
Inconsistencies - Different parts of your app handling the same data differently
Maintenance burden - Changing one thing requires updating five different places
Knowledge silos - Each developer builds everything slightly differently, leading to inconsistencies and inefficiencies.

Ash's solution: Model your application's behavior first, as data, and derive everything else automatically. Ash resources center around actions that represent domain logic. Instead of exposing raw data models, you define meaningful operations like :publish_post, :approve_order, or :calculate_shipping_cost that encapsulate your business logic, validation, and authorization rules. This is coupled with a rich suite of extensions to fill the most common needs of Elixir applications.

Ash fills the gap that brings Phoenix up to feature parity with a batteries included framework like Django. Ash Admin (Django admin), Ash Resource & Domain (Django models & ORM), AshJsonApi (Django REST Framework), Ash Authentication (Django Allauth), Ash Phoenix (Django Forms), Ash Policies (Django Permissions)

But you aren't required to use Phoenix with an Ash project. Ash will happily work as a standalone CLI, terminal app or some other Elixir web framework that comes out tomorrow.

Scott Woodall - Principal Software Engineer, Microsoft

Built for Flexibility

Ash was born out of the battle-scars from inflexible abstractions that eventually paint you into a corner. That's why Ash is designed with multi-tiered configurability and escape hatches all the way down. Instead of deciding that abstraction was bad, we decided that it just needed to be done better. Elixir & the BEAM have our backs, providing a solid foundation upon which to build high quality applications.

You're never locked out of custom behavior. Need to customize how an action works? Use preparations, changes, and validations. Need to override how data is fetched? Implement a manual action. Need to completely bypass Ash for a specific operation? Drop down to Ecto or raw SQL. Need to extend Ash itself? Use the same extension toolkit that powers AshPostgres and AshGraphql.

This isn't accidental - it's core to Ash's design. We provide powerful defaults that work for 80% of cases, extensive configuration options for the next 15%, and escape hatches for the remaining 5%. Your Ash application is just an Elixir application, so when you need to do something completely custom, Ash won't get in your way.

The framework acts as a spinal cord for your application: providing structure and coordination while allowing complete customization at every level.

Essential Context

Elixir Developers

Ash builds on the best of the Elixir ecosystem rather than replacing it. Ash leverages Ecto for database operations, Phoenix for web interfaces, Oban for background jobs, Absinthe for GraphQL, etc. Ash unifies all of this tooling and significantly simplifies and enhances they way you use them together.

Compile-time guarantees come from Ash's declarative nature - many errors that would be runtime failures in other frameworks become compile-time checks in Ash.

The ecosystem advantage: Instead of learning entirely new patterns, Ash enhances familiar Elixir concepts. Your existing knowledge of pattern matching, process supervision, and OTP principles all apply - Ash just provides structure and automation on top, acting as a spinal cord for your application.

Non-Elixir Developers

Elixir is a functional programming language built on the Erlang VM, known for fault-tolerance and concurrency. It's used by WhatsApp, Discord, and Pinterest for systems that need high availability. If you know Ruby or Python, think of Elixir as optimized specifically for distributed, concurrent systems.

Functional vs Object-Oriented: Unlike OOP frameworks, Elixir (and Ash) focus on transforming data through functions rather than encapsulating data in objects. This leads to more predictable, testable code.

Immutability means data doesn't change in-place - instead, you create new versions. This eliminates many common bugs around shared state and makes concurrent operations safer.

Actor Model Concurrency: Instead of threads and locks, Elixir uses lightweight processes (actors) that communicate via messages. This makes Ash naturally suited for high-concurrency applications.

Modules (defmodule) are Elixir's equivalent to classes/namespaces - they group related functions together. Unlike OOP classes, they don't hold state.

New Programmers

Programming languages like Elixir are tools for writing instructions that computers can follow. Elixir is specifically designed for building web applications that can handle lots of users at once.

Modules (the defmodule blocks you'll see) are containers that group related code together. Think of them like chapters in a book - each chapter covers a specific topic.

Business Leaders

Ash reduces software development costs by eliminating repetitive code. When your development team defines a business process once, Ash automatically generates the database structure, API endpoints, and user interfaces - work that normally requires separate specialists.

Faster time-to-market because features that typically take weeks can be built in days. Adding a new feature like "customer reviews" or "order tracking" requires defining the business rules once, rather than building separate systems for web, mobile, and internal tools.

Lower maintenance costs because changes to business rules automatically update all related systems. When you change how orders work, your database, APIs, and documentation stay synchronized without manual updates.

Reduced technical risk through built-in security, data validation, and error handling. Your team spends time building your competitive advantages instead of solving the same infrastructure problems every software company faces.

Developer productivity increases because the framework handles the "plumbing" while your team focuses on what makes your business unique. This means you need fewer developers to build the same functionality.

Eliminates technical debt through enforced consistency. When every part of your application follows the same patterns, there's no accumulation of "quick fixes" and inconsistent approaches that slow down future development and create maintenance headaches.

Faster developer onboarding because new team members learn one set of patterns that apply everywhere. Instead of each developer building things differently, Ash provides a shared vocabulary and approach that new hires can quickly understand and contribute to. Ash is still niche, so developers may not know it right out of the gate, but if you think of Ash as a replacement for your internal framework, which are universally poorly documented and hard to train on, you can see the benefit of Ash being an open source, well documented project with a strong community.

Resources and Actions: The Core Abstractions

The foremost abstraction in Ash is Actions - the things you can do in your domain like :create_user, :publish_post, :approve_order, or :calculate_shipping. These actions are organized into Resources that group related behaviors around domain concepts like User, Post, Order, or Invoice. Using resources, you can easily model actions, alongside the state that they operate on, or just actions in isolation.

These actions are introspectable and fully typed. This means the rest of your application (and extensions - add-on packages that enhance Ash) can automatically understand and build functionality around them. When you define a create action that accepts a :title string and :content text, extensions like AshGraphql can automatically generate GraphQL mutations, AshJsonApi can create REST endpoints, and AshPostgres can handle database persistence - all without additional configuration.

This declarative approach means your resources become the single source of truth for your entire application. Database schemas, API endpoints, authorization rules, state machines, background jobs, and more all stem directly from your resource definitions.

Beyond Simple CRUD

Ash is not a web framework, like Phoenix or Rails. It is a framework for building your application layer, independent of how it is exposed or consumed. It is not an alternative to frameworks like Phoenix, rather a complement to them.

Ash Framework enabled us to build a robust platform for delivering financial services using bitcoin. Ash proved itself to our team by handling innovative use cases with ease and it continues to evolve ahead of our growing list of needs.

— Yousef Janajri, CTO & Co-Founder, Coinbits

The intent behind Ash is not to have you building simple CRUD-style applications, although we do provide conveniences for these cases. The real power comes from defining rich, domain-specific actions with meaningful names like :publish_post, :approve_order, or :calculate_shipping. These actions encapsulate your business logic and can be composed, validated, authorized, and extended in powerful ways.

Model your domain, derive the rest

Ash derives significant portions of your application directly from your resources, with little to no effort required. This allows you to focus on what matters most: your business logic. We leverage the best of the Elixir ecosystem under the hood, providing a single unified tool-chain for our users.

Community

Ash has a vibrant community of developers who contribute to the project, provide support, and share knowledge. Join us on Discord, ElixirForum and GitHub to contribute, ask questions, and stay updated on the latest developments.

Our community is one of the best features of Ash and you should use it. Lots of folks using Ash in production, with a shared mission of making better software.

I'm constantly blown away with the quality of work and support the Ash community has put into this project. It's gotten to the point that I can't imagine starting a new Elixir project that doesn't use Ash.

— Brett Kolodny, Full stack engineer, MEW

An Example: From Simple to Sophisticated

Introduction

If you're the "just show me the code" type, click through these tabs to see an example of evolving a blog post resource over time with Ash & its extensions to get a sense for how it works.

Don't worry about understanding all the code

You're not expected to understand every detail of the syntax - focus on the concepts and how it changes over time. If you want a gentler introduction, head over to the getting started guide.

Actions

# lib/my_blog/blog.ex
defmodule MyBlog.Blog do
  use Ash.Domain

  resources do
    resource MyBlog.Blog.Post do
      # Defines the `analyze_text/1` function which calls
      # the action of the same name on the Post resource.
      define :analyze_text, args: [:text]
    end
  end
end

# lib/my_blog/blog/post.ex
defmodule MyBlog.Blog.Post do
  use Ash.Resource

  actions do
    # Start with pure behavior - a simple action that processes text
    action :analyze_text, :map do
      argument :text, :string, allow_nil?: false

      run fn input, _context ->
        text = input.arguments.text
        words = String.split(text)

        analysis = %{
          word_count: length(words),
          character_count: String.length(text),
          estimated_reading_time: div(length(words), 200) + 1
        }

        {:ok, analysis}
      end
    end
  end
end

Notice how we have not defined any "state" here. A common misconception is that the purpose of Ash is to abstract state. Ash provides tons of useful features around state, but those are features on top of the core concept, which centers around typed actions.

{:ok, analysis} = MyBlog.Blog.analyze_text("This is some sample blog content to analyze.")
# => {:ok, %{word_count: 9, character_count: 49, estimated_reading_time: 1}}

Why not just write a regular function? You could write def analyze_text(text) and get the same result. But here's what the Ash action gives you that a function doesn't:

Type safety - Arguments are automatically validated (try passing a number instead of string)
Introspection - Other tools can discover this action exists and what it does
Extensibility - You can add authorization, logging, or other behaviors later without changing callers
API generation - Extensions can automatically expose this as a REST endpoint or GraphQL query
Consistent interface - All actions work the same way, making your codebase predictable

The action is typed (it knows it takes a string and returns a map) and introspectable (your application can examine it at runtime). This means extensions can automatically understand and build on top of it.

You could stop here

You could stop at this step and still derive significant value from Ash. You wouldn't be using it wrong. You can build your own custom state system under the hood, use Phoenix contexts, call directly into Ecto, totally up to you.

Persistence

Now let's add state to support persistent storage, while keeping our existing behavior:

# lib/my_blog/blog.ex
defmodule MyBlog.Blog do
  use Ash.Domain

  resources do
    resource MyBlog.Blog.Post do
      define :analyze_text, args: [:text]
      define :create_post, action: :create, args: [:title, :content]
    end
  end
end

# lib/my_blog/blog/post.ex
defmodule MyBlog.Blog.Post do
  use Ash.Resource,
    domain: MyBlog.Blog,
    data_layer: AshPostgres.DataLayer # data_layer tells Ash where to store data

  postgres do
    table "posts"
    repo MyBlog.Repo
  end

  attributes do
    uuid_primary_key :id
    attribute :title, :string, allow_nil?: false, public?: true
    attribute :content, :string, public?: true
    attribute :status, :atom, constraints: [one_of: [:draft, :published]], default: :draft, public?: true

    create_timestamp :created_at, public?: true
    update_timestamp :updated_at, public?: true
  end

  actions do
    action :analyze_text, :map do
      argument :text, :string, allow_nil?: false

      run fn input, _context ->
        text = input.arguments.text
        words = String.split(text)

        analysis = %{
          word_count: length(words),
          character_count: String.length(text),
          estimated_reading_time: div(length(words), 200) + 1
        }

        {:ok, analysis}
      end
    end

    defaults [:read, :destroy, create: [:title, :content], update: [:title, :content, :status]]
  end
end

Now your resource combines behavior and state. The original analyze_text action still works, plus you can create and persist posts:

# Behavior still works exactly the same
{:ok, analysis} = MyBlog.Blog.analyze_text("Some text to analyze")

# Now we can also persist state
{:ok, post} = MyBlog.Blog.create_post("My First Post", "This is some content")

GraphQL

This is just one example of an API extension. We also have ash_json_api with more on the way. Ash also comes with all the tools you need to build your own API extension.

# Add to your domain
defmodule MyBlog.Blog do
  use Ash.Domain,
    extensions: [AshGraphql.Domain]

  graphql do
    queries do
      action MyApp.Blog.Post, :analyze_text, :analyze_text
    end

    mutations do
      create MyApp.Blog.Post, :create_post, :create
    end
  end

  # ... resources
end

# Add to your resource
defmodule MyBlog.Blog.Post do
  use Ash.Resource,
    domain: MyBlog.Blog,
    data_layer: AshPostgres.DataLayer,
    extensions: [AshGraphql.Resource]

  graphql do
    # you just tell us the name of the type
    # we can take care of the rest
    # there is deep configuration with plenty of escape hatches
    # for when you need something bespoke
    type :post
  end

  # ... rest of resource definition
end

Now you have a full GraphQL API with queries, mutations, and custom actions automatically generated from your resource definition. That is actually all of the code you need to do it.

The ease of defining our domain model and configuring Ash to generate a powerful GraphQL API has been a game-changer. What used to be complex and time-consuming has become simplicity itself.

— Alan Heywood, CTO, HereTask

Encryption

Cloak is a powerful library for encrypting data at rest and in transit. Ash provides a first class extension that integrates with it directly.

defmodule MyBlog.Blog.Post do
  use Ash.Resource,
    domain: MyBlog.Blog,
    data_layer: AshPostgres.DataLayer,
    extensions: [AshGraphql.Resource, AshCloak.Resource]

  cloak do
    vault MyBlog.Vault
    attributes [:content]  # Encrypt the content attribute
  end

  # ... rest of resource definition
end

Your post content is now automatically encrypted at rest and decrypted when read, with no changes to your existing API or business logic.

State Machines

A state machine is a way to model the valid states for some piece of data. It allows you to define the states a record can be in, and the transitions between those states.

defmodule MyBlog.Blog.Post do
  use Ash.Resource,
    domain: MyBlog.Blog,
    data_layer: AshPostgres.DataLayer,
    extensions: [AshGraphql.Resource, AshCloak.Resource, AshStateMachine]

  state_machine do
    initial_states [:draft]
    default_initial_state :draft

    transitions do
      transition :publish, from: :draft, to: :published
      transition :unpublish, from: :published, to: :draft
    end
  end

  actions do
    # ... same actions as before
    update :publish do
      change transition_state(:published)
      # ... additional custom logic on publish
    end

    update :unpublish do
      change transition_state(:draft)
      # ... additional custom logic on publish
    end
  end

  # ... rest of resource definition
end

Now your posts have a proper state machine with transition actions, state validation, and automatic GraphQL mutations for state changes.

The Ash Advantage

This example demonstrates Ash's core philosophy: Model your domain, derive the rest. Notice how:

The resource definition remained largely unchanged as we added each extension
Each extension automatically understood and enhanced the existing actions
Complex functionality (encryption, state machines, APIs) required minimal configuration
Everything remains introspectable and type-safe
Your business logic stays focused on the domain, not infrastructure concerns
These extensions are built with the same suite of tools we provide to the user for extending Ash. Those using Ash will often end up crafting their own extensions, making the framework truly their own.

Extensions work together seamlessly because they all operate on the same well-defined resource and action abstractions. In the example above, we went from a single action to a full-featured system with database persistence, GraphQL API, encryption, and state management - by adding configuration, not writing code.

The productivity gain is measurable: What normally requires separate database migration files, API endpoint definitions, validation logic, GraphQL schema files, and state management code becomes a single, cohesive resource definition that stays automatically synchronized.

Working with LLMs

LLMs are a new technology, and the patterns on how best to leverage them evolve every day. It is also quite debatable whether it is a good idea to use them at all. Nothing in Ash will ever be predicated on the usage of these tools, but we do want to provide at least some level of base guidance on what we think are the best practices for those that do. This is also to help those who are interested in trying these tools but don't yet know where to start.

This guide is about working with LLM dev assistants, not about building LLM-related features or integrating them into your application. For that, see Ash AI.

Getting Support with LLM generated code

Please note that LLMs often hallucinate despite our best intentions. If you need help with something, and you come to our support channels, you must make it clear when the code you are asking for help with was generated by an LLM. You must first understand the code you've written yourself, and provide a detailed explanation of the code and the issue you are facing when requesting help. The discord and forums are not a place for others to debug LLM hallucinations.

What to know

To take advantage of LLMs, you will want to explore the following. You will have to make up your own mind on which avenues to explore and leverage in the following areas. This is essentially a "big list of stuff you should research on your own".

Language models - OpenAI, Anthropic, Gemini, etc. Choice of language model will make the most difference in your experience.
Agentic editors - Zed, Windsurf, Cursor
Agentic assistants - Claude Code, Aider, Codex
Rules files - The name of these files are often specific to the editor, but they essentially boil down to "stuff to put in the system prompt" to guide the LLM's behavior.

Tools

We suggest setting up, where applicable, the following tools:

Tidewave: Tidewave gives your LLMs the ability to interact with your running application. This can significantly improve the quality of the code generated by LLMs, and allows them to observe and interact with the running application, like reading logs and working with processes.
Ash AI: Ash AI contains tools for building AI enabled applications, but it also comes with a dev MCP server where we will experiment with tools similar to what tidewave offers, but tailored to Ash and the way we work.

Rules

We are working on establishing a pattern whereby packages can provide a usage-rules.md which you can then combine into your own rules file. The idea here is to democratize the process of building rules, allowing you to adopt well vetted and quality rules files from the maintainers of projects. This has only been done for a few packages so far.

To leverage these rules files, you can simply copy them yourself if you'd prefer something more manual, or you can use a new mix task provided by the usage_rules package to combine them into your own rules file.

Combine all of your (direct) dependencies usage rules

mix usage_rules.sync .rules --all

Pick specific dependencies

mix usage_rules.sync .rules \
  ash ash_postgres ash_phoenix ash_graphql ash_json_api ash_ai

You can replace the .rules file with your own current rules file, and it will be appended to the contents. Repeated calls will only replace the package rules contents of the file, not the whole file contents.

Only dependencies of your current project will be added, and any dependencies that don't have rules are skipped.

Glossary

Action

An action describes an operation that can be performed for a given resource; it is the verb to a resource's noun. Examples of actions:

User.create
Comment.delete
BlogPost.publish
Article.search

Ash supports five different types of actions. create, read, update and destroy (collectively often abbreviated as CRUD), and action, referring to a generic action with a custom return type. A resource can define multiple actions per action type, eg. a publish action would be considered an update because it is updating an existing instance of a resource. Actions are much more flexible than simple CRUD, but these five action types serve as templates for anything you might want to do.

See the Actions guide for more.

Actor

The entity that performs an action.

Most actions are run on direct user request, eg. if a user presses a Create button on a page then the actor is the user.

The actor can be anything that you want it to be. It is most typically a map or a struct containing information about the "entity" that is performing the action. In the vast majority of cases, the actor will be something like %MyApp.Accounts.User{}. We recommend that the actor be a struct, but it could also be a map or any other kind of value.

Some example actor types used in practice:

%MyApp.Accounts.User{}
%MyApp.Accounts.Device{}
%MyApp.SystemUser{}

Actors can be used in a number of places, from modifying the behavior of an action to auditing who did what in your system. They are most prominent, however, when writing policies.

See the Actors & Authorization guide for more.

Aggregate

An aggregate is a special type of field for a resource, one that summarizes related information of the record. A more specialized type of a calculation.

If a Project resource has_many Ticket resources, an example of an aggregate on the Project might be to count the tickets associated to each project.

See the Aggregates guide for more.

Attribute

A piece of data belonging to a resource. The most basic building block; an attribute has a type and a value. For resources backed by a data layer, they typically represent a column in a database table, or a key in an object store, for example.

See the Attributes guide for more.

Authorizer

An authorizer is an extension that can be added to a resource that will be given the opportunity to modify and/or prevent requests to a resource. In practice, you will almost always be using Ash.Policy.Authorizer, but you can still write your own if you need to.

See the Actors & Authorization and Policies guides for more.

Calculation

A calculation is a special type of field for a resource, one that is not directly stored in the data layer but generated on-demand. Typically it will derive from other information on the record, but it may come from some other data source entirely.

See the Calculations guide for more.

Changeset

Changesets encapsulate data changes made while creating or updating an instance of a resource. Similarly to Ecto changesets, they include data validations but they also have their own callback hook lifecycle.

See Ash.Changeset for more.

Domain

A method of broadly separating resources into different domains, A.K.A bounded contexts.

See the Domains guide for more.

Extension

A packaged bundle of code that can be included in a resource to provide additional functionality. Built-in functionality such as the resource DSL itself is provided by an extension, and libraries like AshPostgres and AshAdmin also provide extensions that you can add to your resources with just one line of code.

See Extending Resources for more.

Filter

Filters are applied to queries to limit the data returned. They can also be applied to changesets, to ensure only data matching a certain condition is updated. For example:

Fetching Articles that include a certain search term in the title
Fetching Posts created by a specific user
Fetching Tickets updated in the last week
Updating a record only if it's version matches your in memory version (optimistic locking)

See Ash.Filter for more.

Identity

A way to uniquely identify an instance of a resource. A primary key is an example of an identity that is automatically generated; you can manually add others such as a user's email address, or a URL slug for a post. If using AshPostgres, constraints will be created by the migration generator to enforce identities at the database level.

See the Identities guide for more.

Notifier

Notifiers are modules that are called for each action that occurs on a resource (except generic actions). They are called at the end of transactions, meaning that if a notifier is called, it is guaranteed that the action they pertain to has completed successfully.

See the Notifiers guide for more.

Policy

A set of rules defining who is authorized to perform specific actions on a resource. Common policy checks include rules such as:

Forbidding anyone other than the user who wrote a blog post, from editing it
Allowing only admins to update site-wide settings

See the Policies guide for more.

Query

The tools and functions used for reading and filtering stored data, from the data layer.

See Ash.Query for more.

Record

A record is an "instance" of a resource. Keep in mind that this is not an "instance" in a mutable/object-oriented sense, but rather a snapshot of the data at a given point in time. When you call a read action, you get back records. You can provide a record to an update action to determine what data is being updated.

Relationship

Relationships are named links between resources, that define how they relate to each other. Relationships can be used to signify ownership of a record, membership of a group, or can be used in filtering and querying data.

See the Relationships guide for more.

Resource

The central concept in Ash, a resource can be used to model all kinds of things. Most often, they will map to a data store, and represent things like rows of a database table. However, they can also be backed by external data sources, be used for validating data with no persistence at all, or even be simple containers for generic actions, completely stateless.

See the Resource DSL docs for DSL documentation.

Tenant

Multitenancy is the siloing of your app's data into discrete non-overlapping groups, typically by customer or organization (the tenant). Ash supports multitenancy both at the code level and the data layer level (depending on the data layer; for example, AshPostgres uses schemas to fully separate data per tenant.)

See the Multitenancy guide for more.